<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Jetspeed 2 Security - Credentials Management</title>
        <authors>
            <person name="David Le Strat" email="dlestrat@apache.org" />
            <person name="Ate Douma" email="ate@douma.nu" />
        </authors>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Credentials Management Overview">
          <subsection name="DefaultCredentialHandler Features">
            <p>
                With the Jetspeed <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/DefaultCredentialHandler.html">
                <code>DefaultCredentialHandler</code></a> special management of password credentials can
                easily be configured. Through the provided 
                <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/PasswordCredentialProvider.html">
                <code>PasswordCredentialProvider</code></a> and 
                <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptor.html">
                <code>InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptor</code></a> components custom logic can be plugged in for:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>providing a custom 
                    <a href="../jetspeed-api/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/PasswordCredential.html">
                    <code>PasswordCredential</code></a> implementation</li>
                <li>password encoding<br/>
                    If an 
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/CredentialPasswordEncoder.html">
                    <code>CredentialPasswordEncoder</code></a> is available from the 
                    <code>PasswordCredentialProvider</code> passwords will be encoded with it before they are persisted.
                    The provided 
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/MessageDigestCredentialPasswordEncoder.html">
                    <code>MessageDigestCredentialPasswordEncoder</code></a> uses 
                    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/security/MessageDigest.html">
                    <code>MessageDigest</code></a> hash algorithms for the password encryption, and can for example be
                    configured to use <code>SHA-1</code> and <code>Base64</code>.
                </li>
                <li>enforcing password value rules<br/>
                    If an
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/CredentialPasswordValidator.html">
                    <code>CredentialPasswordValidator</code></a> is available from the
                    <code>PasswordCredentialProvider</code>, passwords will be validated with it before they are persisted.
                    The 
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/DefaultCredentialPasswordValidator.html">
                    <code>DefaultCredentialPasswordValidator</code></a> for example enforces non-emtpy password. And
                    with the 
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/SimpleCredentialPasswordValidator.html">
                    <code>SimpleCredentialPasswordValidator</code></a> a minimum length and a minum number of numeric
                    characters can be enforced.
                </li>
                <li>intercepting 
                    <a href="../jetspeed-api/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/om/InternalCredential.html">
                    <code>InternalCredential</code></a> lifecycle events<br/>
                    If the <code>DefaultCredentialHandler</code> is provided with an
                    <code>InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptor</code>, it will invoke this interceptor (or an arbirary
                    set if
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptorsProxy.html">
                    <code>InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptorsProxy</code></a> is used) on:
                    <ul>
                      <li>after loading a credential from the persistent store</li>
                      <li>after authenticating a user</li>
                      <li>before a new credential is saved to the persistent store</li>
                      <li>before a new password is save for the credential</li>                      
                    </ul>
                    Jetspeed already provides a basic set of interceptors, ready to be used:
                    <ul>
                      <li>
                          <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/ValidatePasswordOnLoadInterceptor.html">
                          <code>ValidatePasswordOnLoadInterceptor</code></a><br/>
                          This interceptor can be used to validate (pre)set passwords in the persistent store and force
                          a required change by the user if invalid. It uses the configured <code>CredentialPasswordValidator</code>
                          of the <code>PasswordCredentialProvider</code>, the same as used when a password is changed.
                      </li>
                      <li>
                          <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/EncodePasswordOnFirstLoadInterceptor.html">
                          <code>EncodePasswordOnFirstLoadInterceptor</code></a><br/>
                          This interceptor can be used if passwords needs to be preset in the persistent store or
                          migrated unencoded from a different store. With this interceptor, these cleartext password
                          will automatically be encoded the first time they are loaded from the database, using the 
                          <code>CredentialPasswordEncoder</code> from the <code>PasswordCredentialProvider</code>
                      </li>
                      <li>
                          <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/PasswordExpirationInterceptor.html">
                          <code>PasswordExpirationInterceptor</code></a><br/>
                          This interceptor can be used to enforce a maximum lifespan for passwords.
                          It manages the <code>expiration_date</code> and <code>is_expired</code> members of the
                          <code>InternalCredential</code> and sets the expired flag when on authentication of a user
                          its (valid) password is expired. The authentication will then fail.<br/>
                          Note: A Jetspeed pipeline Valve, the <code>PasswordCredentialValveImpl</code> can be
                          used to request or even enforce users to change their password in time to prevent a password
                          expiration (described further below). 
                      </li>
                      <li>
                          <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/MaxPasswordAuthenticationFailuresInterceptor.html">
                          <code>MaxPasswordAuthenticationFailuresInterceptor</code></a><br/>
                          This interceptor can be used to prevent password hacking by enforcing a maximum number of
                          invalid password attempts in a row. Once this number of authentication failures is reached,
                          the credential will be disabled. On a successful authentication though, this count
                          will automatically be reset to zero again by the <code>DefaultCredentialHandler</code>.
                      </li>                          
                      <li>
                          <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/PasswordHistoryInterceptor.html">
                          <code>PasswordHistoryInterceptor</code></a><br/>
                          This interceptor can be used to enforce usage of unique new passwords in respect to a certain
                          number of previous used passwords. When a new password is set, the current password is saved
                          in a FIFO stack of used passwords. When a user itself changes its password, it must be different
                          from all the onces thus saved, otherwise a 
                          <a href="../jetspeed-api/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/PasswordAlreadyUsedException.html">
                          <code>PasswordAlreadyUsedException</code></a> will be
                          thrown. But setting a new password through the administrative interface still allows any
                          password (when otherwise valid) to be set.
                      </li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>
                    The <code>DefaultCredentialHandler</code> only supports one interceptor to be configured.
                    But, with the 
                    <a href="apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/spi/impl/InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptorsProxy.html">
                    <code>InternalPasswordCredentialInterceptorsProxy</code></a>, a list of interceptors can
                    be configured which then will be invoked sequentially.</p>
                    <p>
                    Jetspeed comes out of the box with several of these interceptors configured, and its very easy to
                    change and extend.See the <a href="config.html#security-spi-atn_xml">security-spi-atn.xml</a>
                    section in the <a href="config.html">Security Services Configuration</a> document for a description
                    of the default configuration. Also provided there is an example how to setup the interceptors to 
                    restore the "old" (and much more restrict) configuration provided with the 2.0-M3 release and
                    earlier.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
          </subsection>
          <subsection name="Credentials Management Implementation">
            <p>
                The class diagram below describes the components used for the
                <code>DefaultCredentialHandler</code>
                implementation.
            </p>
            <p align="center">
                <img src="images/credential-handler-c.gif" border="0" />
            </p>
            <p>
                The OJB mappings for the default credentials implementation are described in 
                <code>security_repository.xml</code>:
                <ul>
                    <li><code>InternalCredential</code>: Maps to the SECURITY_CREDENTIAL table.</li>
                </ul>
                The following database schema is used to stored credentials and their associations to principals.
            </p>
            <p align="center">
                <img src="images/principals-credentials-schema.gif" border="0" />
            </p>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="User interaction">
            <p>
            Although the <code>DefaultCredentialHandler</code> provides fine-grained management of credentials, it cannot
            provide direct feedback to the user like presenting a warning that the current password is soon to be expired.
            But, special request processing pipeline valves provided with jetspeed allow to do just that.</p>
            <p>
            The configuration for these valves can be found and set in the <code>pipelines.xml</code> spring
            configuration file.</p>
            <subsection name="LoginValidationValveImpl">
              <p>
              The <a href="../jetspeed-portal/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/impl/LoginValidationValveImpl.html">
              <code>LoginValidationValveImpl</code></a> provides feedback to the user about the cause of an failed login
              attempt.</p>
              <p>
              It retrieves the <code>UserPrincipal</code> and its current <code>PasswordCredential</code> for the 
              specified user name, and (if found) determines an specific error code based on its state. 
              This error code is communicated back to through the session so an appropriate error message can be
              presented to the user.</p>
              <p>
              The following possible error codes can be returned (all defined in the
              <a href="../jetspeed-api/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/login/LoginConstants.html">
              <code>LoginConstants</code></a> interface):</p>
              <ol>
                <li>ERROR_UNKNOWN_USER</li>
                <li>ERROR_INVALID_PASSWORD</li>
                <li>ERROR_USER_DISABLED</li>
                <li>ERROR_FINAL_LOGIN_ATTEMPT</li>
                <li>ERROR_CREDENTIAL_DISABLED</li>
                <li>ERROR_CREDENTIAL_EXPIRED</li>
              </ol>
              <p>
              Of the above error codes, the <code>ERROR_FINAL_LOGIN_ATTEMPT</code> will only be reported if the valve
              is configured with the same <code>maxNumberOfAuthenticationFailures</code> value as used for the
              related <code>MaxPasswordAuthenticationFailuresInterceptor</code> described above:
              <source><![CDATA[
  <bean id="loginValidationValve"
        class="org.apache.jetspeed.security.impl.LoginValidationValveImpl"
        init-method="initialize">
    <!-- maxNumberOfAuthenticationFailures
         This value should be in sync with the value for
         org.apache.jetspeed.security.spi.impl.MaxPasswordAuthenticationFailuresInterceptor
         (if used) to make sense.
         Any value < 2 will suppress the LoginConststants.ERROR_FINAL_LOGIN_ATTEMPT
         error code when only one last attempt is possible before the credential
         will be disabled after the next authentication failure.
    -->
    <constructor-arg index="0"><value>3</value></constructor-arg>  
</bean>]]>
                </source>
              </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="PasswordCredentialValveImpl">
              <p>
              The <a href="../jetspeed-portal/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/impl/PasswordCredentialValveImpl.html">
              <code>PasswordCredentialValveImpl</code></a> is meant to be used together with a special Portlet on a
              special Portal Page (PSML) to automatically request or even require a user to change its password.</p>
              <p>
              This valve evaluates <code>PasswordCredential.isUpdateRequired()</code> and optionally the 
              <code>expirationDate</code>, <code>lastAuthenticationDate</code> and <code>previousAuthenticationDate</code>
              fields to determine if a user is required or just be asked to change its password.</p>
              <p>
              This valve can optionally be configured with a list of  <code>expirationWarningDays</code> numbers in
              its constructor:
              <source><![CDATA[
<bean id="passwordCredentialValve"
      class="org.apache.jetspeed.security.impl.PasswordCredentialValveImpl"
      init-method="initialize">
 <constructor-arg>
   <!-- expirationWarningDays -->
   <list>
     <value>2</value>
     <value>3</value>
     <value>7</value>
   </list>
 </constructor-arg>
</bean>]]>
                </source>
              These numbers each represent a day before the current <code>expirationDate</code> of the password credential
              when a user should be warned its password is soon to expire and be asked to change it. The
              <code>lastAuthenticationDate</code> and the <code>previousAuthenticationDate</code> are used to determine
              when this should happen. It will be done only once for each configured <code>expirationWarningDay</code>.
              If a user logs on for the first time (after several days) with the above example configuration, 6 days
              before the password expires, he or she will be warned about it. And again when 3 or 2 days are left.</p>
              <p>
              When a user logs on the last day before the password expires <em>or</em> when <code>updateRequired</code>
              is <code>true</code>, the user will be required to change the password, regardless if expirationWarningDays
              are configured or not.</p>
              <p>
              To be able to automatically provide the user with this information and allow or require the password to
              be changed directly after login, a special <code>ProfileLocator</code> 
              <a href="../jetspeed-api/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/profiler/ProfileLocator.html#SECURITY_LOCATOR">
              <code>SECURITY_LOCATOR</code></a> is used. The <code>PageProfilerValve</code> (which should be configed
              <em>after</em> this valve in the pipeline) will then use this enforced locator to be used to find the
              related portal page to present to the user.</p>
              <p>
              For this to work, a <code>"security"</code> Profiler rule must have been setup like the default one 
              provided by Jetspeed:</p>
              <p align="center">
                <img src="images/security-locator.jpg" border="0"/>
              </p>
              <p>
              As can seen from the above image, the default page which will be presented to the user is the
              <code>/my-account.psml</code> located in the root.</p>
              <p>
              This default page contains only one portlet, the <code>ChangePasswordPortlet</code> from the security
              Portlet Application.</p>
              <p>
              The <code>ChangePasswordPortlet</code> works together with the <code>PasswordCredentialValveImpl</code>
              as it checks for the 
              <a href="../jetspeed-api/apidocs/org/apache/jetspeed/security/PasswordCredential.html#PASSWORD_CREDENTIAL_DAYS_VALID_REQUEST_ATTR_KEY">
              <code>PASSWORD_CREDENTIAL_DAYS_VALID_REQUEST_ATTR_KEY</code></a> request parameter which will be set by
              this valve with the number of days the password is still valid. For a required password change this will
              be set to Integer(0).</p>
              <p>
              The default <code>my-account.psml</code> page contains <em>only</em> the <code>ChangePasswordPortlet</code>
              to make sure a user which is <em>required</em> to change the password cannot interact with the portal any
              other way then after the password is changed.</p>
              <p>
              Although the user might be attempted to select a link to a different page (from a portal menu for exampl),
              this valve will make sure only the configured "security" locator page is returned if it is required.
              But, once the password is changed the then targeted page in the url will be navigated to automatically.
              </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Managing Password Expiration">
              <p>
              If the <code>PasswordExpirationInterceptor</code> is used, password expiration for a certain user can be
              directly managed through the <code>UserDetailPortlet</code> provided with the <code>security</code>
              portlet application.</p>
              <p>
              If enabled, this portlet can display the current expiration date of a password and also allows to change
              its value:</p>
              <p align="center">
                <img src="images/password-expiration.jpg" border="0"/>
              </p>              
              <p>
              As you can see, through the radio group, the password expiration date can be changed to:</p>
              <table>
                <tr><th>Action</th><th>Expires</th></tr>
                <tr><td>Expired</td><td>today</td></tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Extend</td>
                  <td>today + <code>maxLifeSpanInDays</code> as configured for the PasswordExpirationInterceptor</td>
                </tr>
                <tr><td>Extend Unlimited</td><td>January 1, 8099 (the maximum value allowed for java.sql.Date)</td></tr>
              </table>
              <p>
              This feature can be enabled through the edit/preferences page of the <code>UserDetailsPortlet</code>:</p>
              <p align="center">
                <img src="images/user-detail-prefs.jpg" border="0"/>
              </p>
              <p>
              Note: when a new password value is specified selected password expiration action <code>Expired</code>
              will be ignored!</p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Setting default 'Change Password required on First Login'">
              <p>
              Through the same <code>UserDetailsPortlet</code> preferences as show above, the default
              <code>updateRequired</code> property of a password credential for a new user can be configured too.</p>
              <p>
              And, if you always need the same setting for all users, you can even suppress the selection box normally 
              displayed on the <code>Add User</code> dialog.</p>
              <p>
              With the preferences set as in the example shown above, the <code>Add User</code> dialog will look like this:</p>
              <p align="center">
                <img src="images/add-user.jpg" border="0"/>
              </p>
              <p>
              A user added with the example preferences set, will have the <code>updateRequired</code> property set to
              true, the <code>User</code> role assigned and use the <code>role-fallback</code> profiling rule.</p>
            </subsection> 
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
