<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
    Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
    
    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Jetspeed 2 Security Architecture</title>
        <authors>
            <person name="David Le Strat" email="dlestrat@apache.org" />
        </authors>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Overview">
            <p>
                Jetspeed 2 security architecture provides a comprehensive suite of security services that can be used to protect a wide ranging type of portal
                resources. The security service implementation is fairly independent of the other portal services and 
                can be reused outside of the portal application.  At its core, Jetspeed 2 security services rely entirely 
                on JAAS to provide authentication and authorization services to the portal:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>Authentication services are implemented through the use of JAAS login modules.</li>
                <li>Authorization services are implemented through the use of custom JAAS policies.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>
                Both authentication and authorization services have been implemented with the goal of providing a direct plugin to the underlying application
                server security framework. Jetspeed 2 can leverage the underlying application server login module as well as through the use of JACC, the
                application server policy management capabilities available in J2EE 1.4 (see
                <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaacc/">API Specifications</a>
                ).
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Jetspeed 2 Security Services">
            <p>
                JAAS defines the contract for authentication and authorization but does not specify any guidelines for the management of the security resources.
                Jetspeed 2 provide a modular set of components aims at providing management functionality for the portal security components.
            </p>
            <p>
                Leveraging Jetspeed 2 component, architecture, the security services provide a set of loosely coupled components providing specialized services:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>UserManager: Service providing user management capabilities.</li>
                <li>GroupManager: Service providing group management capabilities.</li>
                <li>RoleManager: Service providing role management capabilities.</li>
                <li>PermissionManager: Service providing permission management capabilities.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="A Modular and Pluggable Architecture">
            <p>
                Jetspeed 2 security components are assembled using
                <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/injection.html">Dependency Injection</a>
                . By default, Jetspeed uses the
                <a href="http://www.springframework.org">Spring Framework</a>
                as its default IoC container.
            </p>
            <p>
                <img src="images/components.jpg" align="right" border="0" hspace="1" vspace="2" />
                Jetspeed 2 security services are founded on a set of modular and extensible security modules exposed through an SPI model. The SPI model
                provides the ability to modify the behavior of the Jetspeed coarsed security services (UserManager, RoleManager, GroupManager)
                through the modification and configuration of specialized handlers. For
                instance, Jetspeed security services can be configured to retrieve user security principals through the default Jetspeed store or through an
                LDAP store or both.
                <br />
                A
                <code>SecurityProvider</code>
                exposes the configured SPI handlers to the security services. Jetspeed component assembly (based on Spring) architecture provides an easy way to
                reconfigure the security services to satisfy the needs of a specific implementation.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Role Based Access Control">
            <p>
                Role based access control (RBAC) in Jetspeed 2 support multiple hierarchy resolution strategies as defined in
                <a href="http://www.doc.ic.ac.uk/~ecl1/wiki/lib/exe/fetch.php?id=emil%3Aresearchthemes%3Apubbytheme&amp;cache=cache&amp;media=research:papers:1999rbac.pdf">The Uses of Hierarchy in Access Control</a>
                . See <a href="hierarchy.html">Hierarchy Management Overview</a> for more information.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
