<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Portlet 101</title>
		<subtitle>Portal Builder's Knowledge</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="David Dyer"
				email="ddyer@artifact-software.com" />
			<person name="Ron Wheeler"
				email="rwheeler@artifact-software.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Introduction">
			<p>
				Every software development tool requires that the person
				using it has some basic knowledge before they start.
				Jetspeed is no exception.
			</p>
			<p>
				In a typical project, there is a team of people with
				different areas of expertise. In that case, there may be
				some tasks that not everyone on the team would be
				comfortable in executing. This tutorial is designed to
				show the different steps in building a portal and we
				expect that everyone on the team should be able to
				follow this successfully.
			</p>
			<p>
				In order to successfully build this tutorial, we expect
				that each person has some basic skills.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Pre-requisite Knowledge">
			<subsection name="Installing Software">

				<p>
					We expect that you can download and install software
					on your own workstation. This implies that you have
					system administration privileges on your workstation
					and can follow relatively simple instructions. None
					of the software required is difficult to install.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name='Environment variables' />
			<p>
				We expect that you know how to create system-wide
				environment variables on your workstation.
			</p>
			<subsection name='Editing text and XML files'>
				<p>
					You should be able to edit text files and XML files.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section
			name='Skills you might need for developing your own portal'>
			<p>
				Although programming is not required to complete this
				tutorial, you will need to be able to program in order
				to build your own portlets or to add functionality to
				the basic Jetspeed-2 package. In addition, you will need
				to understand a bit about the HTTP Request/Response
				process to understand how a portal communicates with the
				browser.
			</p>

			<subsection name='Programming in Java'>
				<p>
					Portlets are frequently written in Java and you will
					need at least a basic knowledge of Java to modify an
					existing portlet and fairly comprehensive knowledge
					of Java if you want to design a portlet from
					scratch.
				</p>
				<p>
					There are many books and on-line resources for
					learning Java.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name='Developing with JSF'>
				<p>
					JSF can be used to present data and to control
					interactions with the user in a portlet. You will
					need a basic knowledge of JSF to modify an existing
					portlet and fairly comprehensive knowledge of JSF if
					you are designing a portlet from scratch.
				</p>
				<p>
					There are a few books and on-line resources for
					learning JSF.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name='Developing with Velocity'>
				<p>
					Velocity is used extensively in Jetspeed-2 and if
					you need to make changes to the functionality of
					Jetspeed-2, you will need to be able to code in
					Velocity. You will need a basic knowledge of
					Velocity to modify an existing portlet and fairly
					comprehensive knowledge of Velocity if you are
					designing a portlet from scratch.
				</p>
				<p>
					Velocity is a fairly simple language to learn and
					there are very few books and on-line resources for
					learning Velocity.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name='Developing with JSP and Taglib'>
				<p>
					JSP is used extensively in Jetspeed-2 and there is
					an entire module in the tutorial that talks about
					JSP. You will need a basic knowledge of JSP to
					modify an existing portlet that uses JSP and fairly
					comprehensive knowledge of JSP if you are designing
					a portlet from scratch.
				</p>
				<p>
					There are a few books and on-line resources for
					learning JSP.
				</p>
			</subsection>

		</section>
		<section name="Specialist Knowledge">
			<p>
				In the tutorial, we have provided simplied tools for
				data persistence and for hosting the Jetspeed Portal.
				However, most applications require some very specialized
				knowledge that not everyone is required to know. If you
				are going to build a real application with Jetspeed-2
				you will need someone in each of the following areas of
				expertise
			</p>
			<subsection name='Database Technology'>
				<p>
					This includes both the programming and system
					administration aspects of handling data persistence.
					Jetspeed can handle most relational database systems
					as well as higher level tools such as Hibernate.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name='Servlet Engines'>
				<p>
					This includes both the configuring and system
					administration of a serlet engine that can deliver
					Jetspeed-2 functionality over the Internet. Jetspeed
					can run under a number of serlet engines and you
					will need someone who knows how to configure the
					servlet engine and how to deploy a web application
					under it.
				</p>
			</subsection>
						<p>
				<a href='index.html'>Previous</a>
				<a href='01/first-steps.html'>Next</a>
			</p>
			
		</section>
	</body>
</document>