<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Customization</title>
		<subtitle>Decorator and Theme Customization</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="David Dyer"
				email="ddyer@artifact-software.com" />
			<person name="Ron Wheeler"
				email="rwheeler@artifact-software.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Decorator and Theme Customization">
			<p>
				Now that we have created our custom Jetspeed project,
				lets start customizing the portal design. The portal
				design, or skins, are known in Jetspeed as
				<i>decorators and themes</i>
				. With decorators and themes, you can customize the
				portal experience to the branding of your organization.
				In this tutorial, we will simply change a few images,
				CSS styles and colors to get you on your way.
			</p>
			<p>
				It is important to note that all of the changes made in
				this section are made in the build environment. The
				changes we are making here could just as easily be made
				using the portal's live customization features. For
				example, you can drop a decorator or theme into the
				portal while its running. Jetspeed will pick it up
				automatically. Or, to customize a page, you can use the
				portlet customizer or desktop customizer, portlet
				selector, and site manager: all administrative portlets
				that work on your live portal. However, the point of
				configuring everything in a Maven build is to be able to
				easily reproduce portal environments for development,
				testing, and new deployments.
			</p>
			<p>
				This section of the tutorial covers customizing:
				<ul>
					<li>
						Portal Skins (or Decorators). We replace the
						default logo, colors, and page header and
						footers with our own.
					</li>
					<li>
						Portal Themes. Same as Portal Skins, but themes
						apply to the Jetspeed Desktop.
					</li>
					<li>
						Configuring the default portal page to use these
						new decorators and themes
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				Lets get started with customization of the default
				portal page decoration
			</p>
			<p>
				<a href='../01/run-it.html'>Previous</a>
				<a href='page-decoration.html'>Next</a>
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>