<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Administration Portlets</title>
		<subtitle>Welcome to Jetspeed Administration and Security Portlet App</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
<section name="Catalog of Jetspeed Administrative Portlets">
<p>This portlet application provides a rich set of portlets for administering and security a Jetspeed Portal.</p>
<table>
<tr>
<th>Portlet</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AboutJetspeed</td>
<td>Introductory information about Jetspeed for getting started with links to documentation.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CategoryPortletSelector</td>
<td>Portlet Selector for adding portlets to your page. Categories classify portlets by indexed keywords to help users find portlets.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ChangePasswordPortlet</td>
<td>Portlet for changing the password of the current, logged on user.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ContentViewer</td>
<td>Content Viewer displays the content of an HTML, PDF, or other file types from any where on the file system, or relative to the portlet application.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>CustomConfigModePortlet</td>
<td>Provides common custom config mode edit portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DateTimePortlet</td>
<td>Display the date and time in a simple string format.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ForgottenPasswordPortlet</td>
<td>Provides users with the ability to request a new password to be sent to their email address.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ForgottenPasswordReturnPortlet</td>
<td>Provides users with the ability to click and update their password automatically after completing the user registration process.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GroupBrowser</td>
<td>The Group Browser displays a list of groups managed in this portal. From here you can select Groups for editing. Place this portlet on the same page as the Group Details portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GroupDetailsPortlet</td>
<td>The Group Details portlet displays a groups details in a tabbed view. From here you can add, edit, and delete Group information. Place this portlet on the same page as the Group Browser portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>GroupChooser</td>
<td>A Popup portlet for selecting a single group from a list of groups. Usually not placed on a page directly, but accessed by Jetspeed over the portlet pipeline in a popup window.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>JetspeedDeveloper</td>
<td>Introductory information about developing with Jetspeed for getting started with links to development documentation.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LocaleSelector</td>
<td>Locale Selector is a portlet to select your preferred locale (language).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LoginPortlet</td>
<td>Logs a user on to the Jetspeed portal by entering a username and password. Authenticates using full Jetspeed Active Authentication.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>LoginPortletForXHTMLBasic</td>
<td>Login with Active Authentication (XHTML Basic)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortalLoginPortlet</td>
<td>Logs a user on to the Jetspeed portal by entering a username and password. Authentication bypasses JAAS and active authentication.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortalSchemaExporter</td>
<td>The Portal Data Importer, import and export the jetspeed data from jetspeed schema. From here you import/export the users,group,roles and jetspeed objects</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortalSiteManager</td>
<td>The Portal Site Manager displays a hierarchical view of the entire portal site. From here you can add, edit, and delete folders, links, and pages.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortletApplicationLifecyleManager</td>
<td>The PALM (Portlet Application Lifecycle Manager) manages the lifecyle of portlet applications. From here you can start, stop, undeploy and delete portlet applications</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortletApplicationBrowser</td>
<td>The PAM (Portlet Application Manager) Portlet Application Browser displays a list of portlet applications deployed to this portal. From here you can add, edit, and delete portlet applications. Place on same page as Portlet Application Details</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortletApplicationDetail</td>
<td>The PAM (Portlet Application Manager) Portlet Application Detail displays a specific portlet application deployed to this portal. From here you can add, edit, and delete portlet applications. Place on same page as Portlet Application Browser</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>PortletTracking</td>
<td>Portlet Tracking Manager to track the state of portlets that are not being responsive. Allows you to disable the rendering of specific portlets.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ProfilerAdmin</td>
<td>The Profiler Admin portlet is used to administer profiling rules. You can create new rules, edit rules and delete rules and criterion.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RoleBrowser</td>
<td>The Role Browser displays a list of roles managed in this portal. From here you can select Roles for editing. Place this portlet on the same page as the Role Details portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RoleChooser</td>
<td>A Popup portlet for selecting a single role from a list of roles. Usually not placed on a page directly, but accessed by Jetspeed over the portlet pipeline in a popup window.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RoleDetailsPortlet</td>
<td>The Role Details portlet displays a roles details in a tabbed view. From here you can add, edit, and delete Role information. Place this portlet on the same page as the Role Browser portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RoleMultiChooser</td>
<td>A Popup portlet for selecting one or more roles from a list of roles. Usually not placed on a page directly, but accessed by Jetspeed over the portlet pipeline in a popup window.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>RPADPortlet</td>
<td>Remote Portlet Application Deployer for Jetspeed. Deploy portlets from remote locations on the internet into this portal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SecurityConstraintsPortlet</td>
<td>Declartive Security Constraint editor. Manages PSML global security constraints to grant or deny access to pages and folders.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SecurityPermissionsPortlet</td>
<td>Policy Editor for managing the Jetspeed JAAS Security Policy. The policy is a standard Java security policy (JAAS), stored in a database. Portlet, page, and folder permissions are managed here.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SSOBrowserPortlet</td>
<td>SSO Sites Browser displays a list of all configured SSO sites in the portal. From here you can select SSO Sites for editing. Place this portlet on the same page as the SSO Details portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>SSODetailsPortlet</td>
<td>The SSO Site Details portlet edits the credentials and site location for a single SSO Site. Place this portlet on the same page as the SSO Browser portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>StatisticsPortlet</td>
<td>Provides statistics about portal access hits by page, portlet, and by user. Statistical results are sorted by highest hit rate.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UserBrowserPortlet</td>
<td>The User Browser displays a list of users managed in this portal. From here you can select users for editing. Place this portlet on the same page as the User Details portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UserDetailsPortlet</td>
<td>The User Details portlet displays a users details in a tabbed view. From here you can add, edit, and delete User information. Place this portlet on the same page as the User Browser portlet.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UserChooser</td>
<td>A Popup portlet for selecting a single user from a list of users. Usually not placed on a page directly, but accessed by Jetspeed over the portlet pipeline in a popup window.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UserMultiChooser</td>
<td>A Popup portlet for selecting one or more users from a list of users. Usually not placed on a page directly, but accessed by Jetspeed over the portlet pipeline in a popup window.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UserRegistrationPortlet</td>
<td>Provides users with the ability register as a new user with the portal.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>WelcomeToJetspeed</td>
<td>Information about the current release of Jetspeed.</td>
</tr>
</table>	
</section>
</body>
</document>