<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Tutorial</title>
		<subtitle>The Jetspeed Complete Tutorial</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
    <section name="Welcome to the Jetspeed Tutorial!">
      <p> 
		The Jetspeed Tutorial is a step-by-step set of instruction and source code for 
		creating a custom Jetspeed Portal from scratch. 
      </p>	
      <p> 
		When starting a new Jetspeed portal project, 
		we strongly recommend that you create a custom portal project, 
		and do not edit the Jetspeed-2 source and resources directly.         
      </p>	
	  <p>
	    This tutorial will guide you through the steps to create a sample portal named <b>jetexpress</b>.
	    The goal of this tutorial is to prepare you for creating your own custom Jetspeed portal,
	    complete with your own set of portal pages, your company logos and text, your own set of portlet applications,
	    and any special integration required to run inside Jetspeed.	   
	  </p>	          
	  <subsection name='Prerequisites'>
	   The tutorial requires the following software installed on your system:
	   <ul>
	     <li>Java 1.4 or higher</li>
	     <li>Maven-2</li>	 
	     <li>An internet connection so that Maven can download plugins</li>
	   </ul>
	  <p>
	    Before getting started with the tutorial, review the Custom Build commands available to you:
	    <ul>
	    <li><a href='build-commands.html'>Build Commands</a></li>
	    <li><a href='project-generation.html'>Project Generation Archetypes</a></li>
	    <li><a href='project-directory.html'>Project Directory Overview</a></li>
	  	</ul>
	  </p>
	  </subsection>	  
	  <subsection name='Tutorial Resources'>	  	  
	  <p>
	    During the tutorial, at times you will be asked to copy files from the <i>resources</i> directory.
	    You can cut and paste the <i>copy | cp</i> commands (for Windows and Linux) into a shell,
	    and copy the resources into your new custom portal project. These commands are not really
	    a part of the normal development cycle, but are there to demonstrate the incremental changes 
	    to the portal as we progress through the tutorial.
	  </p>
	  <p>
	    To get started with the tutorial, click here: <a href='01/first-steps.html'>Start Tutorial</a>
	  </p>
	  </subsection>
	  </section>
	</body>
</document>