<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Getting Started with Jetspeed 2</title>
		<subtitle>Getting up and running quickly</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Where do I start?">
		<p>Where you start depends on what you plan on doing with Jetspeed. Its always best to start by reading the documentation guides. There are several guides provided:
		</p>
					<ul>
						<li>
							<a href="usersguide/index.html">
								Users Guide
							</a>
						</li>
						<li>
							<a href="adminguide/index.html">
								Administration Guide
							</a>
						</li>
						<li>
							<a href="deployguide/index.html">
								Deployment and Configuration Guide
							</a>
						</li>
						<li>
							<a href="devguide/index.html">
								Developers Guide
							</a>
						</li>
						<li>
							<a href="deploy/index.html">
								Deployers Guide
							</a>
						</li>
					</ul>
		<p>
		For those of you in more of a hurry to get started,		
				you have the choice of
				installing Jetspeed from a binary release or doing more indepth open source development by working with the
				source code.</p><p>If you want to modify the core functionality of
				Jetspeed or contribute to the development of Jetspeed,
				you need to work with the source code. If you are 
				interested in building your first custom enterprise
				portal, try the custom build. We recommend trying an Evaluation (demo, download) to get started. Eventually you will want to move on to Building a Custom Portal.
				Advanced users will want to learn how to build from source.
		</p>
		<ul>
		  <li><a href="#Evaluating">Evaluation</a></li>
		  <li><a href="#Custom Build">Building a Custom Portal</a></li>
		  <li><a href="#Building from Source">Building Jetspeed from Source</a></li>
	   </ul>	   		  
		</section>
		<section name="Evaluating">
		<p>
		If you are evaluating Jetspeed, best to download the latest distribution or try running Jetspeed from the demo site:
		<ul>
		  <li><a href="download.html">Download Jetspeed</a></li>
		  <li><a href="demo.html">Jetspeed Online Demos</a></li>
	   </ul>		  
		</p>
		<p><b>Download Requirements</b> - The requirements for the downloadable distribution are: Java 1.4.2_02 or higher, enough memory to run Tomcat with several web apps (the demo comes with Tomcat embedded in the installer)</p> 
		<p><b>Online Demo Requirements</b> - The requirements for the online demos are minimal: just a web browser</p> 
		</section>
		<section name="Custom Build">
			<p>
When starting a new Jetspeed portal project, we strongly recommend that you create a custom portal project, and do not edit the Jetspeed-2 source and resources directly. 
A custom build allows you to create and maintain a Jetspeed Portal's lifecycle. With a custom build, you have a reproducible procedure for maintaining your portal across future versions. 
When we say custom, we mean customizing Jetspeed for your needs. Everyone has custom requirements. Custom build procedures formalize the steps required to create a custom portal. 
Although Jetspeed can be customized online using the portal customization features. Still, having a reproducible build is valuable as it  enables you to store artifacts in a source code repository and 
maintain the life-cycle of this source.
</p>
<p> 
Custom Jetspeed builds for version 2.1.3 can currently be built with Maven-1, Maven-2 or Ant. Building Jetspeed from the source is not necessary for most projects.
Since Maven-1 is being deprecated out of Jetspeed in version 2.2, we recommend starting with either an <a href="#Ant Custom Build">Ant Custom Build</a> or 
a <a href="#Maven-2 Custom Build">Maven-2 Custom Build</a>.
</p> 
<subsection name="Ant Custom Build">
<p>The Ant Custom Build is a set of build targets for creating and maintaining a portal. You can easily hook the Ant build into a developer's portal running locally for development, 
a test or staging server, or a production server. The Ant Custom Build provides you with several goals including:
<ul>
<li>Create an Installer</li> 
<li>Deploy Portlet Applications</li> 
<li>Deploy Decorations </li>
<li>Deploy Site and Page modifications</li> 
<li>Deploy Spring Assembly modifications </li>
<li>Upgrade to a new version </li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
To get started, goto the Ant Tutorial found here: <a href="tutorials/ant/index.html">Ant Tutorial for Jetspeed 2.1.3</a>
</p>	
</subsection>
<subsection name="Maven-2 Custom Build">
<p>The Maven-2 Custom Build is based on a Maven-2 plugin. To get started with the Maven-2 plugin, see the tutorial and usage guide here:
<ul>
<li><a href="tutorials/maven-2/index.html">Maven-2 Custom Build Tutorial</a></li>
<li><a href="devguide/m2-build/maven-2-custom.html">Maven-2 Custom Build Guide</a></li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
<i>There is also a deprecated Maven-1 plugin. If you really insist on using Maven-1 custom builds, see the docs here: <a href="devguide/m1-build/getting-started-binary.html">Maven-1 Custom Build Guide</a>.</i> 
</p>	
</subsection>
<subsection name="Requirements for Custom Builds">
<p>
The general requirements for all custom builds of 2.1.3 are:
</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Java 1.4.2_02 or higher</li>
		<li>Maven-1 or Maven-2</li>
		<li>Ant</li>
		<li>
			Servlet 2.4 Engine:
				<ul>
						<li><a href="deployguide/guide-tomcat.html">Tomcat 5.5.x</a></li> 
						<li>Jetty</li>
						<li><a href="adminguide/websphere/index.html">Websphere 6.0</a></li>
						<li>Geronimo</li>
						<li>JBoss</li>
						<li>Weblogic</li>
				</ul>
				Jetspeed 2 portals can be run under any
				servlet container supporting the 2.4 specification or
				greater. However we don't have documentation listed for all servers. Contributions welcome! 				
		</li>
		<li>A Database
				Jetspeed's security model requires a database to
				authorize users and to retain the user information.
				Jetspeed security should work with any JDBC 2.0
				compliant driver. The following databases are tested:
				<ul>
 				    <li>Derby</li>
					<li>HSQLDB - Hypersonic SQL</li>
					<li>MySQL</li>
					<li>Oracle</li>
					<li>Postgres</li>
					<li>DB2</li>
					<li>Sybase</li>
					<li>SQL Server</li>
				</ul>
			<p>
				Jetspeed is distributed with the Derby database
				configured as the default.
				</p>
			<p>
				The database configuration will be setup during the
				custom build process based on your property settings. See the appropriate build guide for details.. If you are not going to use the
				default Derby database, you need to select another database
				during your build configuration.
			</p>
				
		</li>		
	</ul>			
</subsection>
</section>
<section name='Building from Source'>
			<p>
	Building from Source is covered in the following Developer guides for either Maven-1 or Maven-2. For most cases, we recommend building with Maven-2, but the Maven-1 build is also fully supported.
	If you are going to build a 2.1.3 installer, currently you must build with the Maven-1 build.
	</p>
	<subsection name="Building from Source with Maven-1">
	<ul>
	<li>
				<a href="devguide/m1-build/getting-started-source.html">
					Building with Maven-1 from Source
				</a>
	</li>				
	<li>
				<a href="devguide/m1-build/getting-started-binary.html">
					Maven-1 Plugin Guide 
				</a>
	</li>				
	</ul>
	</subsection>				
	<subsection name="Building from Source with Maven-2">
	<p>The best place to start using Jetspeed, as a Developer, is to go to the developers guide documentation:</p>
	<p><a href="devguide/index.html">Jetspeed Developers Guide</a></p>
	<p>For general build information, also see:</p>
	<ul>
	<li>
				<a href="devguide/m2-build/maven-2-build.html">
					Building with Maven-2 from Source
				</a>
	</li>				
	<li>
				<a href="devguide/m2-build/j2-maven-plugin.html">
					Maven-2 Plugin Guide
				</a>
	</li>				
	</ul>
	</subsection>				
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
