<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
	
	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>
			Getting Started with Jetspeed 2 using a Binary Release
		</title>
		<subtitle>Getting ready to build your own portal</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Ate Douma" email="ate@apache.org" />
			<person name="David Le Strat" email="dlestrat@apache.org" />
			<person name="Ron Wheeler"
				email="rwheeler@artifact-software.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="1. Some Basic Information">
			<subsection name="Basic Assumptions">
				<ul>
					<li>
						Unless otherwise specified, you should be
						running all maven build commands from within the
						Jetspeed directory (if you are just building
						Jetspeed) or from within your custom portal
						directory.
					</li>
					<li>
						You must use "/" as a file seperator on both
						*nix and windows, e.g. c:/windows, and /home.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Maven">
				<p>
					We will not go into the specifics of Maven as that
					is beyond the scope of this document. If you have
					never used Maven, you need to read
					<a
						href="http://maven.apache.org/what-is-maven.html">
						"What is Maven"
					</a>
					just to get a sense of the role of Maven in a
					software development project. If your project
					involves more than one or two people, you may want
					to look into
					<a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a>
					in more detail since it does simplify and
					standardize many of the project management issues
					that are commonly encountered.
				</p>
				<p>
					Here are a few bits of standard maven jargon we feel
					is important for you to know.
				</p>
				<p>
					You will see mention of a
					<i>maven repository</i>
					in this document. When you install Maven the .maven/
					directory is created in your ${USER_HOME) directory.
					<br />
					Under .maven/ you will see a
					<i>repository</i>
					directory. This is were Maven stores all of the jars
					that it downloads when you run your builds. This is
					also were Maven puts your jars and wars that you
					build.
					Jar files will be stored in a directory structure
					that has the format of
					${groupId}/${projectId}/jars/${projectId}-{$version}.jar.
					The portal war file is stored as
					${groupId}/${projectId}/wars/${projectId}.war. The
					${groupId}, ${projectId} and ${version} variables
					are discussed later on in this document. Jar and war
					files will also be created in your project in the
					<i>/target</i>
					directory.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Variables">
				<p>
					Variables are represented as ${
					<i>some_variable</i>
					}. Variable names are case sensitive. Variables are
					defined in several places in a Maven project and
					according to the
					<a
						href="http://maven.apache.org/reference/user-guide.html##Maven_Setup">
						Maven Setup
					</a>
					section of the on-line Maven User's Guide, the
					properties files in Maven are processed in the
					following order:
					<ul>
						<li>
							${project.home}/project.properties -
							Properties that are common to the entire
							project
						</li>
						<li>
							${project.home}/build.properties -
							Properties that describe the current release
						</li>
						<li>
							${user.home}/build.properties - Properties
							that are particular to you
						</li>
					</ul>
					The usage of these files is quite different from the
					way they are used in a project that develops from
					the sources since the project in that case is the
					Jetspeed project rather than your own portal. In
					that case, the user's build.properties is used much
					more intensively used to override Jetspeed's
					parameters.
				</p>
				<p>
					Maven processes this sequence of properties files,
					overriding any previously defined properties with
					newer definitions. The last definition wins! In this
					sequence, your ${user.home}/build.properties has the
					final say in the list of properties files processed.
				</p>
				<p>
					This list of properties files that Maven processes
					is called the "standard properties file set".
				</p>
				<p>
					In addition, System properties are processed after
					the standard properties files. So, a property
					specified on the command line using the
					-Dproperty=value convention will override any
					previous definition of that property.
				</p>
				<p>
					For example, ${org.apache.jetspeed.server.home}
					references either:
					<ul>
						<li>
							a property defined earlier in the standard
							properties file set,
						</li>
						<li>
							a property specified on the command line of
							the Maven invokation,
						</li>
						<li>
							a variable that has been defined somehwere
							within the build process or
						</li>
						<li>
							a variable defined in another build file
							within Jetspeed.
						</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Installation dependent locations">
				<p>
					The documentation refers to some common locations by
					the following names:
				</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						<b>${USER_HOME}</b>
						: This is the user's home directory. For Windows
						systems, this generally c:\Documents and
						Settings\${userName} where ${userName} is the
						name you use to log into windows.
						<br />
						${user.home} is synonymous with ${USER_HOME}
						within this document.
					</li>
					<li>
						<b>${CATALINA_HOME}</b>
						: This refers to the location of your tomcat
						installation, e.g.
						<i>c:/tomcat</i>
						.
					</li>
				</ul>
				<p>
					These are not used in the Jetspeed configuration but
					are merely shorthand notations to make the
					documentation more concise and precise.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Subversion (SVN)">
				<p>
					<a href="http://subversion.tigris.org">
						Subversion (SVN)
					</a>
					is used in the Jetspeed project to manage the source
					files. SVN is very similar to CVS. For those user's
					on Windows system who prefer non-command line access
					we suggest using
					<a href="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org">
						TortoiseSVN
					</a>
					which plugs into your Windows Explorer view. For
					those using the Eclipse IDE, the
					<a href="http://subclipse.tigris.org">Subclipse</a>
					plugin is available for SVN access.
				</p>
			</subsection>

		</section>

		<section name='2. Overview of the Jetspeed build Process'>
			<p>
				Setting up a custom portal development project using the
				binary distribution is a fairly simple process. At the
				end, you will you have a directory structure and set of
				files that will simplify building and deploying your own
				custom portal.
			</p>
			<p>
				If you want to setup a Jetspeed portal application using
				Eclipse as your IDE, you should continue reading this
				page for background material but refer to
				<a href="Portal-Development-with-Eclipse.html">
					Building a Jetspeed Enterprise Portal with Eclipse
				</a>
				for the actual instructions on using Eclipse for
				Jetspeed 2 portal development.
			</p>
			<p>
				Creating your own custom portal is very easy with the
				maven plugin provided by Jetspeed 2. The steps are:
				<ul>
					<li>Download and install the Jetspeed plugin</li>
					<li>
						Use the plugin to download and generate the
						Jetspeed binary distribution.
					</li>
					<li>
						Customize the properties files to reflect your
						database installation and local environment.
					</li>
					<li>Prepare the Application Server</li>
					<li>Build the portal</li>
					<li>Start the Database Server(if required)</li>
					<li>Initialize the Database</li>
					<li>
						Deploy the default portal using your database
					</li>
					<li>Test the default portal</li>
					<li>
						Customize the default portal to include your
						logo and Portal name
					</li>
					<li>
						Generate, deploy and test your custom Portal
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<p>
				The Jetspeed 2 maven-plugin defines default values for
				most of the properties you can set, but not all. As you
				customize the portal, you will override others.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="3. Installation Steps">
			<subsection name="3.1 Download the Jetspeed Plugin">
				<subsection
					name="3.1.1 Set the maven remote repository lookup configuration">
					Now we're going to configure your
					${user.home}build.properties file to give Maven the
					information that it needs to download the Jetspeed-2
					maven-plugin. The base directory where you are going
					to build your portal needs to be specified to Maven
					as well as the the maven remote repository need to
					be configured properly in your
					<code>${USER_HOME}/build.properties</code>
					:
					<source><![CDATA[basedir = c:/myportal
maven.repo.remote = http://www.bluesunrise.com/maven/, http://www.ibiblio.org/maven/, \
http://dist.codehaus.org/, http://cvs.apache.org/repository]]>
					</source>
					<i>
						Note: the order in which the repositories are
						specified is significant!
					</i>
				</subsection>
				<subsection
					name="3.1.2 Install the Jetspeed 2 maven-plugin">
					<p>
						The first time, and when you want to upgrade to
						a newer version of Jetspeed 2, you need to
						install the maven-plugin as follows:
						<source>
							<![CDATA[
maven -DartifactId=maven-jetspeed2-plugin -DgroupId=org.apache.portals.jetspeed-2 -Dversion=2.0 plugin:download]]>
						</source>
						<i>
							Note: you must set the version to the
							specific version you want to install,
							"2.0-M3" is just an example.
						</i>
					</p>
				</subsection>
			</subsection>

			<subsection
				name="3.2 Download the default Jetspeed portal project">
				<p>
					Once you have the maven-plugin installed and set
					properties as needed, generate a default portal
					configuration using the plugin as follows:
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
maven j2:portal.genapp]]>
					</source>
					<i>
						This maven goal actually executes several
						subgoals which are further described in the
						<a href="j2-maven-plugin.html">
							maven-plugin documentation
						</a>
						itself.
					</i>
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name="3.3 Customize the properties files">
				<p>
					You can fill in as much of the project information
					in the project.xml file as you want. This will
					depend on how you intend to use Maven as a project
					management tool and is beyond the scope of this
					document. The information in the project.xml file
					distributed with Jetspeed reflects the Jetspeed
					development project.
				</p>
				<p>
					You can now customize the properties files to
					reflect your database installation and local
					environment.
				</p>
				<p>
					The
					<code>${basedir}project.properties</code>
					file provided by the Jetspeed developers includes
					all of the variables that are common to all portals
					based on Jetspeed. You should not have to change
					these.
				</p>
				<p>
					The project properties are described in the
					<a
						href="http://maven.apache.org/maven-1.x/reference/properties.html">
						Maven Properties Reference
					</a>
					documentation. We have already filled in the value
					for basedir and maven.repo.remote in previous steps.
					You can fill in as much of the project information
					in the
					<code>${basedir}project.xml</code>
					file as you want. This will depend on how you intend
					to use Maven as a project management tool and is
					beyond the scope of this document. The
					<a href="http://maven.apache.org/maven-1.x">
						Maven site
					</a>
					has all of the information that you need to use
					Maven successfully.
				</p>
				<p>
					The configuration of your specific properties needs
					to be done before we can build the portal. Review
					the definition of the configuration properties
					described in
					<a href="configuration-properties.html">
						Basic Configuration Parameters
					</a>
					.
				</p>
				<p>
					In the case of a binary build, the basic
					configuration properties can be placed in
					<code>${basedir}build.properties</code>
					. A minimal custom portal configuration using the
					default HSQLDB database can be something like:
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
# required portal configuration properties          
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home           = /home/myportal/
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.groupId        = myprojects
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.artifactId     = myportal
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.name           = My Test Portal
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.currentVersion = 1.0

]]>
					</source>
				</p>
				<p>
					If you are not using the HSQLDB database that comes
					pre-configured in the
					<code>${basedir}project.properties</code>
					file, you also need to define the database
					parameters in the
					<code>${basedir}build.properties</code>
					file. Refer to the
					<a href="guide-database.html">Database Configuration</a>
					section for a description of the variables required.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="3.4 Prepare the Application Server">
				Before running the portal, we need to prepare the
				Application server to run a Jetspeed portal. This
				consists of telling Jetspeed where the application
				server expects files to be placed and what
				authentication values are required to request service
				from the Application Server's management tools. There
				may also be modifications to the server configuration so
				be sure to read the
				<a href="guides/guide-app-servers.html">
					Application server configuration documentation
				</a>
				.
				<p>
					Verify that you made the Application Server changes
					suggested in the overview of the
					<a href="getting-started.html">Getting Started</a>
					documentation.
				</p>
				<p>
					A minimal custom portal configuration using the
					Tomcat 5.5 Application Server could be something
					like:

					<source>
						<![CDATA[
# required portal configuration properties          
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home           = /home/myportal/
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.groupId        = myprojects
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.artifactId     = myportal
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.name           = My Test Portal
org.apache.jetspeed.portal.currentVersion = 1.0

# required application server properties
org.apache.jetspeed.server.home                      = ${CATALINA_HOME}/
org.apache.jetspeed.server.shared                    = ${org.apache.jetspeed.server.home}/shared/lib/
org.apache.jetspeed.deploy.war.dir                   = ${org.apache.jetspeed.server.home}/webapps/
org.apache.jetspeed.services.autodeployment.user     = j2deployer
org.apache.jetspeed.services.autodeployment.password = xxxxx
org.apache.jetspeed.catalina.version.major           = 5.5]]>

					</source>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="3.5 Build the portal">
				<p>
					Once your portal configuration and setup is ready,
					you can build and install the portal application in
					your local maven repository (as needed for
					deployment) using the following standard maven goal
					from your custom portal project directory (in
					${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}):
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
maven war:install]]>
					</source>
				</p>
				<p>
					You are now ready to deploy the new portal
					application. For this, skip the following section on
					building the Jetspeed 2 portal from source and
					continue with the
					<a href="#6__Deploy_and_Run">deployment</a>
					section.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="3.6 Start the Database Server">
				<p>
					You need to make sure that your database server is
					running. If you are not using the default HSQLDB
					database, you need to make sure that it is running
					and that the user that will own the Jetspeed tables
					is setup and ready for use. Refer to the
					<a href="guide-database.html">Database Configuration</a>
					section for more information. If you are using the
					default HSQLDB database you need to start it before
					deploying the portal.
				</p>
				<p>
					To start the HSQLDB production database run the
					following in a
					<i>separate</i>
					console:
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
cd ${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}
maven j2:start.production.server]]>
					</source>
				</p>
				<p>
					You need to have this database running during the
					deployment and while running the application server.
					Afterwards you can stop the database and close this
					console with a
					<code>Ctrl-C</code>
					.
				</p>
				<p>
					Note: this is required when using the
					<code>j2:quickStart</code>
					goal as described below. The Jetspeed 2 maven-plugin
					provides other (sub)goals which you can use without
					(re)creating a production database and/or inserting
					default portal configuration data. See the
					<a href="j2-maven-plugin.html">
						Plugin documentation
					</a>
					for further information about the available goals.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="3.7 Initialize the Database">
				<p>
					The database's tables and initial data needs to be
					loaded prior to Jetspeed being deployed. The
					<a href="j2-maven-plugin.html">maven-plugin</a>
					includes a number of goals that can be used to
					manage the database. The easiest way to load the
					tables and deploy the application is to run the
					j2:quickstart goal.
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
cd ${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}
maven j2:quickStart]]>
					</source>
					This can only be run once without a bit of a cleanup
					afterwards since it defines the tables and loads the
					data as part of starting the application. If you
					have an error and you want to run it again, you must
					make sure that the tables and data are cleaned out
					either by manually dropping the tables in the
					database or by using the j2:db.drop.production Maven
					goal.
				</p>
				<p>
					The j2:quickstart currently only covers deploying to
					Tomcat 5 or Tomcat 5.5 application servers.
				</p>
				<p>
					Information about deployment to other application
					servers can be found at the The Jetspeed 2
					<a
						href="http://wiki.apache.org/portals/Jetspeed2">
						Wiki
					</a>
					.
				</p>
				<p>
					To deploy a default Jetspeed 2 portal, including the
					demo portlet applications, run the following in a
					<i>separate</i>
					console:
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
cd ${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}
maven j2:quickStart]]>
					</source>
					<i>
						Note: the
						<a href="j2-maven-plugin.html">
							maven-plugin documentation
						</a>
						described other goals you can use to initialize
						the database.
					</i>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection
				name="3.8 Deploy the default portal using your database">
				<p>
					The j2:quickstart task does this for you. If you
					have used another Maven goal to initialize the
					database, then you can deploy the portal by using:
				</p>
				<source>
					<![CDATA[
cd ${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}
maven j2:fullDeploy]]>
				</source>
				<p>
					The j2:fullDeploy goal currently only covers
					deploying to Tomcat 5 or Tomcat 5.5 application
					servers.
				</p>
				<p>
					Information about deployment to other application
					servers can be found at the The Jetspeed 2
					<a
						href="http://wiki.apache.org/portals/Jetspeed2">
						Wiki
					</a>
					.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="3.9 Test the default portal">
				<p>
					The final step in getting the default portal running
					is starting up your Tomcat server. The portal will
					automatically install any deployed portlet
					applications.
				</p>
				<p>
					Then you can access the portal with your browser at:
					<source><a href="http://localhost:8080/jetspeed">http://localhost:8080/jetspeed</a></source>
					or replace "jetspeed" in the above url with the name
					of your own portal application (
					<code>
						${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.artifactId}
					</code>
					).
				</p>
				<p>
					If you see a running Jetspeed portal, we have
					succeeded in getting the software installed and
					working.
				</p>
				<p>
					With the default Jetspeed 2 portal deployment,
					several example user accounts are inserted into the
					portal database with which you can logon to the
					portal:
					<table>
						<tr>
							<th>username</th>
							<th>password</th>
							<th>roles</th>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<code>admin</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>admin</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>admin, manager, user</code>
							</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<code>manager</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>manager</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>manager, user</code>
							</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<code>jetspeed</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>jetspeed</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>manager</code>
							</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<code>user</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>user</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>user</code>
							</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<code>tomcat</code>
							</td>
							<td>
								<code>tomcat</code>
							</td>
							<td></td>
						</tr>
					</table>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection
				name="3.10 Customize the default portal to include your logo and Portal name">
				<p>
					Now that the default portal is working we can try a
					small customization to test out the customization
					process. We are going to change the logo and portal
					name.
				</p>
				<subsection
					name="3.10.1 Creating your customization area">

					<p>
						The first step is to create a directory to hold
						your customized files. This will help you to
						preserve your changes when you install new
						versions of jetspeed. Create a directory in the
						top level of the portal home.
					</p>
					<source>
						<![CDATA[
cd ${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}
mkdir customized]]>
					</source>
					<p>
						Make a copy of the build.properties file that
						you have already modified.
					</p>
					<p>
						You may also want to make a directory to hold
						the original files before you modify them. This
						is not strictly requirred since you can always
						reload the distribution. However it might be
						handy to keep a copy for reference or to quickly
						get back to the state before you made changes.
					</p>
				</subsection>
				<subsection
					name="3.10.2 Making some simple cuistomizations">
					<p>
						We are going to change the logo and the portal
						name to test customization. You can make you own
						logo to replace the Jetspeed logo. Take a look
						at the ${basedir}/src/webapp/images/logo.png to
						get the size and to verify the background
						colour. Make your own logo or copy the
						testlogo.png file to your
						<code>${basedir}/customized</code>
						directory.
					</p>
				</subsection>
			</subsection>

			<subsection
				name="3.11 Generate, deploy and test your custom Portal">
				<p>

				</p>
				<source>
					<![CDATA[
cd ${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.home}
maven j2:fullDeploy]]>
				</source>

				<p>
					You can access the revised portal with your browser
					at:
					<pre>
						<a href="http://localhost:8080/jetspeed">
							http://localhost:8080/jetspeed
						</a>
					</pre>
					or replace "jetspeed" in the above url with the name
					of your own portal application (
					<code>
						${org.apache.jetspeed.portal.artifactId}
					</code>
					).
				</p>
				<p>
					You should see the new name and the new logo on the
					front page.
				</p>

			</subsection>


		</section>
	</body>
</document>
