<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
	
	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>How to Help?</title>
		<subtitle>How to Help?</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Le Strat" email="dlestrat@apache.org" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="How to Help?">
		<subsection name="Simple Things I Can Do to Help">
		<p>
		There are many ways to help with Jetspeed-2 as with most open source projects:
		<ul>
		<li>Subscribe to the <a href="mail-lists.html">user mailing list</a> and help answer questions from the community.
		In open source a thriving community makes the project successful.  Don't be shy to ask basic questions, we have all
		been there.</li>
		<li>Report bugs and issues that you encounter in <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/secure/BrowseProject.jspa?id=10492">Jetspeed-2 bug tracking system</a>.
		Prior to reporting a bug, make sure to discuss the issue on the <a href="mail-lists.html">user mailing list</a> or even the 
		<a href="mail-lists.html">developer mailing list</a>.</li>
		<li>When you encounter an issue, you may be compelled to fix it.  We encourage this as this makes for a vibrant
		community.  Once you have a fix, <a href="guides/guide-j2-development.html">submit a patch</a> on the reporting issue.</li>
		</ul>
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Why Should I Get Involved?">
		<p>
		There are many reasons why you want to help, just a few strong points:
		<ul>
		<li>If you help others solve there issues, they will most likely help you when you run into some problems.</li>
		<li>By contributing patches, you can influence the prioritization of functionality and get your changes incorporated.</li>
		<li>By reporting issues, you help Jetspeed-2 become a stronger project and improve its quality overall.</li>
		<li>You will meet and get to know great people as well as share and learn best practices which will help you on
		your project.</li>
		</ul>
		We are looking forward to have you part of our community!
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="How do I Join the Project?">
		<p>
		Projects at Apache operate under a <a href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html#meritocracy">meritocracy</a>.
		To become a committer, you first need to demonstrate your committment.  The best way to do so is to start contributing patch,
		participate in the community and make your interest known.  It takes time and willingness to help and contribute!  This may
		seem a bit intimidating at first, but the community will always help people who show interest and committment.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subection name="Other Resources for Help">
		<p>
		Here are some useful links for other resources for help.
		<ul>
		<li><a href="http://portals.apache.org/development/code-standards.html">Portals project coding standards</a>.</li>
		<li><a href="http://portals.apache.org/development/documentation.html">Portals project documentation standards</a>.</li>
		<li><a href="http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html">How does the Apache Software Foundation work</a>?</li>
		<li><a href="http://people.apache.org/~coar/mlists.html#portals.apache.org">Portals mailing lists statistics</a>.  This can be helpful
		to help you decide which mailing list to subscribe to.</li>
		</ul>
		</p>
		</subection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>

