<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
	
	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>For Jetspeed-1 Users</title>
		<subtitle>For Jetspeed-1 Users</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Le Strat" email="dlestrat@apache.org" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="For Jetspeed-1 Users">
	    <p>Jetspeed-2 is a new project, written from groundup and does not have any dependencies on Jetspeed-1.		   
		   Jetspeed-2 is based on industry standards, designed for high-volume enterprise portals applications.
		   The foremost difference is Jetspeeds Component Oriented Architecture, all assembled together with Spring.
		   Components replace Turbine services with a standardized component model. 
		   Deployment of new portlet applications, which was completely missing in Jetspeed-1, 
		   is implemented to the Portlet API specification. Turbines file-based configuration 
		   for properties are replaced managed components. Jetspeed-2 is fully decoupled from 
		   the legacy projects that were intertwined in the Jetspeed-1 architecture.
		   </p>
		</section>
		<section name="Whats New in Jetspeed-2">
			<ul>
			<li>1.	Fully Compliant with Java Portlet API Standard</li>
			<li>2.	Separation of Portlet Applications From Portal</li>
			<li>3.	Live Deployment Model for Portlet Applications and Portal Layouts</li>
			<li>4.	Spring Component Based Architecture</li>
			<li>5.	Multi-threaded Portlet Aggregation Engine</li>
			<li>6.	Scalable Architecture</li>
			<li>7.	Pipeline-based Request Processing</li>
			<li>8.	JAAS Security</li>
			<li>9.	Bridges Integration with Struts, JSF, PHP, Perl, Velocity</li>
			<li>19.	CMS-based Site Navigations</li>	
		</ul>				
		</section>
		<section name="Whats the same in Jetspeed-2">		
			<p>Not much.</p>
			<p>
			In fact Jetspeed-2 does not re-use any of the code in Jetspeed-1. 
			Some concepts are continued in Jetspeed-2, but with new design and implementations. 
			The table below shows some of the concepts continued in Jetspeed-2 from Jetspeed-1. 
			Note that even though the concepts are continued, they are have changed, 
			in some cases significantly:
				</p>
			<ul>
			<li>1.	PSML – Portlet Structured Markup Language. 
				    Defines the layout of portlets on a page. 
				    While the purpose is still the same, the XML format has changed. 
				    Porting is possible, requires a migration tool. 
				    PSML now fits into an overall Jetspeed Navigation Site as a page-type resource.
				    No PSML porting tool is currently available. However, an XSLT transform could be a good choice.
			</li>	
			<li>2.	Portal Wide Security Policy and Constraints – Jetspeed-2 has two kinds of security 
				    mechanisms: JAAS-based security policies, and declarative security constraints 
				    much like Jetspeed-1 constraints. Where as Jetspeed-1 constraints were limited
				    to PSML, Jetspeed-2 declarative security constraints are also applied to folders
				    and links.</li>
			<li>3.	Portlets – Portlets now must adhere to the new Portlet API. 
				    No porting tool is currently available. 
				    The Jetspeed-1 Portlet API will not be continued in Jetspeed-2.
				    </li>
			<li>4.  Turbine Services are out (Fulcrum). Jetspeed-2 is based on Spring components.</li>	
			<li>5.  Registries – The Jetspeed-1 Registries are discontinued in Jetspeed-2. 
				    All portlets are now stored in a Registry database in Jetspeed-2. 
				    No porting tool is available. 
				    Recommend converting your portlets to JSR-168 portlets, 
				   packaging all portlets in a portlet application, 
				   and deploying as standard WAR file. 
				   Other registries are all deprecated.</li>
			<li>6. JSP and Velocity Templates – Templates can be re-used to some extend. 
				   Any references to Rundata or any other Turbine or Jetspeed-1 tools or 
				   tags must be converted.</li>				
			<li>7. Controls and Controllers – These concepts have changed, and are now called 
				   decorators and layouts. The Turbine module concept, which backed controls 
				   and controllers, is no longer supported. Layouts and decorators are now 
				   only implemented as portlets, or as just plain markup. Layouts and templates 
				   can be deployed to the portal as a deployable unit.</li>
			<li>8. Jetspeed Configurations and Jetspeed Component Assemblies replace Property Files. 
				   Component (services) should be assembled, not defined in property files. 
				   Many of the features in Jetspeed-1 were represented as read-only properties in 
				   the Jetspeed-1 static property files. Jetspeed-2 components can be configured with JMX.</li>
			</ul>
			</section>
			<section name='Turbine Gone'>
				<p>
				Jetspeed-1 is tightly coupled to the Turbine MVC-2 framework, and this coupling permeates 
				many areas of the Jetspeed API.  Jetspeed-2 does not rely on Turbine as the MVC-2 controller. 
				Instead, we follow the separation of concerns pattern, and concentrates on doing one thing and doing it well. 
				That is, implementing a portal. Where as Jetspeed-1 coupled MVC Controller, portal engine, and portlet container 
				all into one deeply coupled servlet, Jetspeed-2 separates these concerns clearly in its architecture. 
				The portal engine is Jetspeed-2. It is the MVC for page aggregation, leveraging the dispatching nature 
				of the servlet architecture, and delegating the actual rendering of portlets to portlet application frameworks.  
				These portlet applications can in turn have their own MVC frameworks, such as Struts portlet applications, 
				JSF portlet applications, or Turbine portlet application frameworks.				
				</p>
			</section>
		    <section name='RunData No More'>
				<p>
				Most notably missing from Portlet API portlets is the RunData class. 
				The Jetspeed-1 API uses the RunData class ubiquitously, serving as a wrapper for both the servlet request and response. 
				Other dependencies on Turbine include Portlet Actions, Portlet Aggregation Engine (ECS), 
				the Service Architecture, Configuration and Turbine Modules. None of these exist in the newer version.
				</p>					
				<table>
					<tr>
					<th>Jetspeed-1</th>
					<th>Jetspeed-2</th>
					</tr>	
					<tr>
						<td>Run Data</td>
						<td>Portlet API: Portlet Request and Portlet Response</td>						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Portlet Aggregation Engine (ECS)</td>
						<td>Jetspeed-2 Multi-threaded Portlet Container Engine</td>						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Turbine Service Architecture</td>
						<td>Jetspeed-2 Components</td>						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Property Configuration Files</td>
						<td>Spring Configurations, JMX</td>						
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Turbine Modules (Actions)</td>
						<td>Portlet API Actions </td>						
					</tr>
					
				</table>
			</section>
			<section name='Pluto is the Portlet Container'>
				<p>The Jetspeed-2 portal does not implement the Portlet container. 
					<a href='http://portals.apache.org/pluto'>Pluto</a> implements the JSR 168 interface 
					contract for portlets running inside our portal.
					The Pluto container handles all communication with portlets for the portal. 														
				</p>					
			</section>
		    <section name='Aggregating, Isnt It?'>
				<p>The aggregation engine and the Jetspeed-1 Portlet API are both coupled to a deprecated Jakarta package ECS 
					(Element Construction Set). ECS generates HTML with Java code, storing the content in temporary 
					Java objects before sending the HTML out to the servlet output stream. This wasteful use of Java objects 
					leads to fragmentation on memory, accelerated garbage collection, and paging in high volume sites. 
					The servlet API clearly provides a content stream for streaming out portlet content.  Jetspeed-2 models 
					its aggregation engine upon the Portlet APIs streams and readers, analogous to the stream-based Servlet 
					API for rendering content.</p>
			</section>
		    <section name='State and Life Cycle'>
				<p>The Portlet API clearly defines the lifecycle of a portlet, the event sequences for actions, 
				   and how the container can cache content from a portlet. The Portlet Lifecycle was not clearly 
				   defined in Jetspeed-1. The portlet API clearly states that only one instance of a portlet will 
				   reside in memory inside a container. The state of the portlet is directly related to the servlet state 
				   for the current user session. While this may seem obvious, portlet state and lifetime was not clearly 
				   defined in Jetspeed-1.					
				</p>
			</section>
			<section name='Actions'>
				<p>In version 1, actions were coupled to Turbine and not properly integrated into the Portlet class. 
					In fact, actions were separate objects from portlets. In the Portlet API, actions are methods on the portlet. 
					Action event handling and sequencing is clearly defined in the specification.</p>
			</section>
		    <section name='Standard Deployment'>
				<p>Jetspeed-1 does not have a standardized method of deploying portlets and their supporting files, 
					commonly referred to as portlet applications. In order to import an application, one must package 
					registry files, class and jar files, PSML and templates so that they match the Jetspeed web application format.</p>
				<p>In Jetspeed-2, the Portlet API defines a standard deployment descriptor for deploying Portal Applications into Jetspeed. 
					Portal applications must be deployed to the portal. Analogous to the servlets packaged in a web-application (WAR)
					 deployment model, portals support portlets packaged in a portal-application deployment model. 
					The Portal Application archive follows the same format as the WAR format defined in the Servlet specification 
					with an additional Portlet deployment descriptor file. The clear advantage in Jetspeed-2 is the ability to deploy 
					live portlet applications to the server in a standardized format.</p>
			</section>
		    <section name='Resources and Deployment'>
				<p>Jetspeed-1 resources such as portal templates, images, skins, controllers, controls, are all merged into the single 
				   Jetspeed web application with no deployment model. For example, to override the default skin or top banner, the 
				   resource files are copied into the portal directory, property files updated to point to the new resources, and the 
				   server must be restarted. This made for the process of tailoring Jetspeed-1 portals to real production portals 
				   a process of property and file merging. In fact Jetspeed-1 now has a Maven plug-in to manage production portals 
				   separately from the core Jetspeed-1 portal. The need for this kind of tool covers up the fact that Jetspeed-1 
					is missing a good deployment model for portal resources, requiring difficult portal maintenance procedures.</p>
				<p>For a Jetspeed-2 production portal, portal resources are packaged in a Jetspeed-specific archive format. 
					Thus portal resources (top banners, skins, images, style sheets) can all be deployed to dynamically tailor 
					the portal at runtime.</p>
			</section>
		    <section name='the Standard'>
				<p>JSR168 is the Portlet specification enables interoperability between Portlets and Portals. 
					The specification defines a set of APIs that addresses standardization of portlet aggregation, 
					personalization, presentation and security.  The goals of JSR168 are to: </p>
				<ul>
					<li>Define common Portal metaphor </li>
					<li>Define a standard Portlet Java API </li>
					<li>Ensure interoperability and portability</li>
					<li>Enable multiple markups support </li>
					<li>Ensure compatibility with other technologies </li>					
				</ul>
				<p>The Jetspeed-2 Portlet Server supports the JSR 168 standard. 
				   This is an important initiative, introducing true portlet portability.</p>
			</section>
	</body>
</document>

