<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Copyright 2004 The Apache Software Foundation
	
	Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
	you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
	You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed 2 Home Page</title>
		<subtitle>Welcome to Jetspeed 2</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="David Le Strat" email="dlestrat@apache.org" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="What is Jetspeed?">
			<p>
				Jetspeed is an Open Source implementation of an
				Enterprise Information Portal, using Java and XML. A
				portal makes network resources (applications, databases
				and so forth) available to end-users. The user can
				access the portal via a web browser, WAP-phone, pager or
				any other device. Jetspeed acts as the central hub where
				information from multiple sources are made available in
				an easy to use manner.
			</p>
			<p>

				The data presented via Jetspeed is independent of
				content type, This means that content from for example
				XML,RSS or SMTP can be integrated with Jetspeed. The
				actual presentation of the data is handled via ates XSL
				and delivered to the user for example via the
				combination of Java Server Pages (JSPs) and HTML.
				Jetspeed provides support for templating and content
				publication frameworks such as
				<a href="http://cocoon.apache.org">Cocoon</a>
				,
				<a href="http://www.webmacro.org/">WebMacro</a>
				and
				<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">
					Velocity
				</a>
				. Note that outside of regular browser Jetspeed also
				supports WAP devices.
			</p>
			<p>
				Jetspeed helps you build portal applications quickly.
				The goal is to make Jetspeed a tool for both portal
				developers as well as user interface designers.
				Currently the focus is on providing developers with a
				set of tools that facilitates building the base for the
				portal. With Jetspeed you can quickly build an XML
				portal and also syndicate your own content.

			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>