<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="taylor@apache.org">David Sean Taylor</author>
    <title>Apache Portals</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Welcome to the Apache Portals Project">

    <p>
    <b>Apache Portals</b> is a collaborative software development project dedicated to providing robust, 
    full-featured, commercial-quality, and freely available Portal related software on a wide variety 
    of platforms and programming languages. This project is managed in cooperation with various 
    individuals worldwide (both independent and company-affiliated experts), 
     who use the Internet to communicate, plan, and develop Portal software and related documentation.
    </p>
    <p>
      For more information on getting started with Apache Portals, see the
      <a href="getting-started.html">Getting Started</a> guide.
    </p>
    

<subsection name="About Portals">
<p>
Modern software is complex and expensive, 
which has motivated many companies to invest in enterprise portals as a mechanism by 
which they can manage information in a cohesive and structured fashion.  
</p>
<p>
Portals offer many advantages over other software applications.  
First, they provide a single point of entry for employees, partners, and customers.  
Second, portals can access Web services transparently from any device in virtually any location.   
Third, portals are highly flexible; they can exist in the form of B2E intra-nets, B2B extra-nets, or B2C inter-nets.   
Fourth, portals can be combined to form a portal network that can span a companys entire enterprise system, 
allowing for access both inside and outside the firewall.
</p>
<p>
Portals have many advantages, which is why they have become the de facto standard for Web application delivery.  
In fact, analysts have predicted that portals will become the next generation for the desktop environment.   
</p>
<p>
Portals distinguish themselves from other software systems because they provide the ability to integrate disparate 
systems and leverage the functionality provided by those systems.  
As such, they are not mutually exclusive, and do not force you into an either-or decision vis-a-vis existing software systems.  
This point is of paramount importance, particularly when you consider the fact that Web services are destined to fuel the 
explosion of Web applications.  Since portals can access any Web services, the conclusion is inescapable:  
portals provide a unique opportunity to leverage the functionality of nascent technologies as well as mature, 
well-established software systems.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Jetspeed-1">
  <p>
    <a href="http://portals.apache.org/jetspeed-1/">Jetspeed-1</a> is an Open Source implementation of an 
    Enterprise Information Portal, using Java and XML. Jetspeed-1 is a user-customizable portal system, supporting
    a rich feature set and mature user base. 
  </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Jetspeed-2">
  <p>
    <a href="http://portals.apache.org/jetspeed-2/">Jetspeed-2</a> is the next-generation enterprise portal at Apache.
    Jetspeed-2 offers several architectural enhancements and improvements over Jetspeed 1.0. 
    First, Jetspeed-2 is conformant to the <a href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=168">Java Portlet Standard</a> and will provide a standard mechanism for the deployment of portlets.  
    Second, Jetspeed-2 has matured to a more scalable architecture featuring multi-threaded functionality.  
    Third, Jetspeed-2 is decoupled from several legacy open source projects.  
    Fourth, Jetspeed-2 is based on a component architecture.
  </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Pluto">
  <p>
  <a href="http://portals.apache.org/pluto/">Pluto</a> is the Reference Implementation of the Java Portlet Specification. 
  The current version of this Portlet specification is <a href="http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=168">JSR 168 1.0</a>
  Portlets are designed to run in the context of a portal. They are written to the Portlet API.
  Pluto implements the contract, the Portlet API, between portlets and portals.
  Pluto is a portlet container.
  </p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="WSRP4J">
  <p>
  <a href="http://portals.apache.org/wsrp4j/">WSRP4J</a> is the Reference Implementation of the 
  <a href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=wsrp">Oasis WSRP Specification</a>. 
  The OASIS Web Services for Remote Portlets (WSRP) standard simplifies integration of remote applications/content into 
  portals so that portal administrators can pick from a rich choice of services and integrate it in their portal 
  without programming effort. 
  As a result, WSRP becomes the means for content and application providers to provide their services to 
  organizations running portals in a very easily consumable form.
  </p>
</subsection>

</section>

</body>
</document>
