<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Group Administration Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Administering Groups</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Group Administration Guide">
			<p>
				Administering groups with Jetspeed. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Group Management is where you manage the creation and removal of groups for users and roles. This interface can also be used for adding users
				to groups and removing individual or multiple users from group membership. 
				The Group Management page is located inside the Jetspeed Administrative Portlets section. 
				The Group Management page is the third tab on the administrative menu across the top. Here you see the Group Admin which is located on 
				the left of the two portlets displayed when initially accessing this area.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="The Group Browser">
			<p>
				<img src="images/groupbrowser.png"/>		
			</p>
			<subsection name="Searching">
			<p>
					You can search for a particular group by entering the group name or start of the group name
					in the search text box. After clicking on the "Search" button, the group listing
					will show the search results starting with the group that best matched your search
					query. Groups that are listed normally after the matched search result will still be displayed.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Filtering">
			<p>
					To get only exact matches when searching for a particular group name, check the "filter"
					checkbox below the search text box. Clicking on the "Refresh" button will reset the group listing to the first page. 
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Selecting for Edit">
			<p>
					Select one of the groups in the listing for editing by clicking on the group name.
					A small arrow will appear in front of the group name to indicate it is currently
					selected, and the group's details will be loaded in the Group Detail Information
					portlet.
			</p>
			</subsection>		
		</section>
		<section name="Adding a New Group">
			<p>
			You may add a group by entering the name in the Group Name field of the Group Detail Information Portlet and clicking Save.  The Group Admin portlet on the left will update 
			to include the new name alphabetically. You can use the Users and Roles tabs to add users and roles to your new group.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Removing a Group">
			<p>
				You may remove a group by selecting a group for edit in the Group Admin portlet.  The Group Detail Information portlet will update to include 
				an option for remove.  Any users or roles that are members of that group will not be affected any other way.  Adding a group of the same name 
				will not reinstate the users or roles membership automatically.  Roles and Users must be added again for them to belong to the group.	
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Group Detail Information">
		<p>
			<img src="images/groupedit.png"/>
		</p>
		<p>
			The following sections are based on a group having been selected for editing as described above. Two tabbed menu's, Users and Roles, are 
			available for editing within the group.
		</p>
		<subsection name="Add Users to Group">
		<p>
			With the Users tab active, click the "Add User to Group..." button located below.  A new pop-up window
			will appear with a list of available users.  Select the checkboxes of any user you wish to add to the group and click "Add Users". Multiple selections are possible by clicking on the 
			checkboxes individually. The window 
			will automatically refresh with the new users listed.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Remove Checked Users">
		<p>
			Checkboxes to the left of each user in the list can be checked to select the user.  Multiple selections are possible by clicking on the 
			checkboxes individually.  Click the "Remove Checked Users" button to remove the selected users.  The window will update itself after 
			performing the action.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Search Users in Group">
		<p>
			You can search for a particular user in a group by entering the user name or start of the user name
			in the search text box. After clicking on the "Search" button, the Users in Group listing
			will show the search results starting with the user that best matched your search
			query. Users that are listed normally after the matched search result will still be displayed.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Add Roles to Group">
		<p>
			With the group selected for editing and the Roles tab active, click the "Add Roles to Group..." button located below.  A new pop-up window
			will appear with a list of available roles.  Select the checkboxes of any roles you wish to add to the group and click "Add Roles".  Multiple selections are possible by clicking on the 
			checkboxes individually. The window 
			will automatically refresh with the new users listed.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Remove Checked Roles">
		<p>
			Checkboxes to the left of each role in the list can be checked to select the role.  Multiple selections are possible by clicking on the 
			checkboxes individually.  Click the "Remove Checked Roles" button to remove the selected roles.  The window will update itself after 
			performing the action.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Search Roles in Group">
		<p>
			You can search for a particular role in a group by entering the role name or beginning part of the role name
			in the search text box. After clicking on the "Search" button, the Roles in Group listing
			will show the search results starting with the role that best matched your search
			query. Roles that are listed normally after the matched search result will still be displayed.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		</section>	
	</body>
</document>