<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Import/Export Administration Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Administering Import/Export</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
	<section name="Import/Export Administration Guide">
		<p>
			The Import/Export Service Portlet can be used to export properties to an xml file or to import properties from an xml file.
		</p>
		<p>
			<img src="images/import_export.png" />
		</p>
		<subsection name="Export">
		<p>
			There are four sections that can be exported together or individually using this portlet. User/Groups/Roles, Profiling Rules, Capabilities and 
			Permissions are available to export as an xml file. Click the section or sections you wish to retrieve and click the Export button.  A new link 
			will appear to the right of the Export button titled "Download".  Clicking on the Download link display the xml contents exported in your browser window.
		</p>
		<p>
			Save the xml file in your browser window with the Save As option as type xml.  The name of the file defaults to tmpExport.xml, rename and save 
			to an appropriate location.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Export Preferences">
		<p>
			A second section in Export is known Export Preferences.  Export Preferences will retrieve the portlet preferences currently configured in Jetspeed.
		</p>
		<p>
			Save the xml file in your browser window with the Save As option as type xml.  The name of the file defaults to tmpExport.xml, rename and save 
			to an appropriate location.
		</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Import">
		<p>
			Import will allow you to retrieve one of your previously exported xml files or another file properly formatted in xml for Jetspeed.  
			Click the Browse button and your browsers window open dialogue window will allow you to navigate your system for the file.  Locate the file and 
			click open.  The file will now be displayed in the Choose file to import field.  Click on the Import button to finish the process.  A "File 
			imported successfully" message will appear just below the Import word in the portlet window.   
		</p>
		</subsection>
	</section>
	</body>
</document>