<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Portlet Application Lifecycle Administration Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Administering Portlet Application Lifecycle</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Portlet Application Lifecycle Administration Guide">
		<p>
			The Portlet Application Lifecycle Manager can be found in the Jetspeed Administrative Portlets Tabbed Menu named PALM. This Administrative 
			portlet can be used to manage portlets deployed from war files that were added through RPAD or are part of the default installation.
		</p>
		<p>
			<img src="images/palmmain.png"/>
		</p>
		<p> 
		<table>
					<tr>
						<th>Field</th>
						<th>Description</th>            
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Name</td>
						<td>Corresponds to the Artifact ID from the <a href="rpad.html">RPAD portlet.</a></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Version</td>
						<td>Defaults to 1.0.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Path</td>
						<td>The path is the location of the portlet files in relation to the webapps folder of the Application Server.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Running</td>
						<td>Shows the status of the Portlet.  True or False values.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Commands</td>
						<td>Actions to take on the portlet listed in the same row.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td> </td>
						<td>Start</td>
						<td>Starts a portlet that has been stopped using the stop command, will not start an undeployed portlet.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td> </td>
						<td>Stop</td>
						<td>Changes the state of a running portlet from true to false. Portlet will remain on pages they were previously added.</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td> </td>
						<td>Undeploy</td>
						<td>Disables the portlet. Portlet must be redployed from <a href="rpad.html">RPAD</a> before it can be started again.  Portlet is still available in Add Portlets section</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td> </td>
						<td>Delete</td>
						<td>Removes the portlet from the list of portlets and removes from the list of portlets in the Add Portlet section.</td>
					</tr>
				</table>
		</p>
		<p>
			Each of the commands start, stop, undeploy and delete will display a warning message in a drop down window that will ask you to confirm your action.
		</p>
		<p>
			<img src="images/palmmessage.png"/>
		</p>
		<p>
			Required portlets will have their Commands section without clickable links to prevent disabling Jetspeed.
		</p>
	</section>
	</body>
</document>