<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Permissions Administration Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Administering Security Permissions</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Security Permissions Administration Guide">
			<p> 
Security permissions restrict access to resources in the portal. Portal resources (folders, links, pages, portlets) can be secured with either:
<ul>
<li>Security Constraints (based on Jetspeed-specific security constraints)</li> 
<li>Security Permissions (based on a Java Security Policy)</li>
</ul> 
The default security is Constraints as they are easier to configure by a portal administrator. The advantage of Permissions is that they 
are stored in a central repository in the Jetspeed database, and  they adhere to the Java Security Standard.  Both constraints and permissions inherit. Meaning that if you set a 
permission or constraint on a folder, it is inherited by all subfolders and pages. Permissions are an implementation of a Java Security Policy stored in a database.  
</p>
<p>
A permission grants a permission to a security principal, either: 
<ul>
<li>a role</li> 
<li>a group</li> 
<li>a user</li> 
<li>or * for all users</li>
</ul> 
A permission defines the action, which can be standard portlet modes:
<ul> 
<li>view</li> 
<li>edit</li> 
<li>help</li>
</ul> 
Or Jetspeed extended portlet modes: 
<ul> 
<li>edit_defaults</li> 
<li>about </li>
<li>config </li>
<li>print</li> 
</ul>
</p>
<subsection name="Permission Management">
<p> 
TODO: describe UI, screen shots
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Permission Usage">
<p> 
A security definition is referenced by portal resources to secure that particular resource. The following resources can be secured: 
<ul>
<li>Folder: in the folder metadata</li> 
<li>Page: in a PSML file </li>
<li>Link: in a .link file </li>
<li>Portlet Window: one instance of a portlet on a page</li>
<li>Portlet Definition: all instances of a portlet on all pages</li>
<li>Portlet Application: all portlets in a portlet application</li>
</ul>
Securing a resource is as simple as defining a permission definition using the administrative portlet defined above. You can do this from several areas of the portal:
<ul>
<li>1. The Site Manager to secure a folder, page or link</li>
<li>2. Portlet Application Manager, to secure a Portlet Application or Portlet Definition</li>
<li>3. Config Mode, if available for a portlet, you can secure a portlet instance</li>
</ul>
Additionally, portlets can be secured in the deployment descriptors. See the <a href="">deployment</a> guide for more details.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
	</body>
</document>