<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
	contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
	this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
	The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
	(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
	the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
	distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
	WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
	See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
	limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Role Administration Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Administering Roles</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
			<person name="Jeff Maddux" email="jmaddux@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Role Administration Guide">
			<p>
			Role Management is where you manage individual portal roles. You can create new roles and remove existing roles.
			You can assign users to roles. The Role Management page is located inside the Jetspeed Administrative Portlets section.
			The Role Management page is the second tab on the administrative menu across the top. Here you see the Role Admin
			on the left, and the Role Detail Information on the right. 																						
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Role Admin">
			<p>
			The Role Admin portlet lists all portal roles and allows you to search for a particular role.
			</p>
			<p>			
			TODO: screenshot of complete role admin portlet 								
			</p>
			<subsection name="Paging">
				<p>
				If there are more than ten roles in the system, the role listing is spread over several pages each displaying ten roles.
				You can navigate through the pages using the buttons right below the listing.
				Clicking on the "Refresh" button will reset the role listing to the first page.
				</p>
				<p>				
				TODO: screenshot of paging buttons 			
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Searching">
				<p>
				You can search for a particular role by entering the role name or part of the role name in the search text box.
				After clicking on the "Search" button, the role listing will show the search results, starting with the role that
				best matched your search query, followed by increasingly less matching roles.
				</p>
				<p>				
				TODO: screenshot of search text box and button 			
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Filtering">
				<p>
				To get only exact matches when searching for (or part of) a particular role name, check the "filter" checkbox below the
				search text box.
				</p>
				<p>				
				TODO: screenshot of the filter check box 			
				</p>
			</subsection>		
		</section>
		<section name="Adding and Deleting Roles">
			<p>
			The Role Detail Information portlet allows you to add and/or remove roles.
			</p>
			<p>
			TODO: screenshot of role admin and role detail information portlet
			</p>
			<subsection name="Adding a Role">
				<p>
				To add a role, depending on the Role Detail Information portlets state, you either need to...
	                <ul>
	                    <li>enter a role name and press "Save", or</li>
	                    <li>select "Add New Role", enter a role name and press "Save",</li>
	                </ul> 					
				</p>		
				<p>
				TODO: screenshot of two states of Role Detail Information portlet
			
				<table>
				<tr>
				<th>Field</th>
				<th>Description</th>			
				</tr>
				<tr>
				<td>New Role Name</td>
				<td>Sets the name for role</td>
				</tr>
				</table>
				</p>
			</subsection>		
			<subsection name="Removing a Role">
				<p>
				To remove a role from the system, click on the desired role in the Role Admin portlet. A small arrow will appear in front of the
				role name to indicate it is currently selected, and the role's existing users will be loaded in the Role Details Information portlet.				
				Click the "Remove Role" button. Be aware that this action is permanent!
				</p>
				<p>			
				TODO: screenshot of Remove Role button		
				</p>
			</subsection>			
		</section>		
		<section name="Adding Users to Roles">
			<p>	
			To add or remove users assigned to a role, click on the role name in the Role Admin portlet. A small arrow will appear in front of the
			role name to indicate it is currently selected, and the role's existing users will be loaded in the Role Details Information portlet.					
			</p>
			<p>			
			TODO: screenshot of role admin and role detail information portlet	
			</p>
			<subsection name="Paging">
				<p>
				If there are more than ten users assigned to a role in the system, the role listing is spread over several pages
				each displaying ten users. You can navigate through the pages using the buttons right below the listing.
				Clicking on the "Refresh" button will reset the user listing to the first page.
				</p>
				<p>				
				TODO: screenshot of paging buttons 			
				</p>
			</subsection>				
			<subsection name="Add Users to Role">
				<p>
				The Role Detail Information portlet allows you to add users to a role. Select "Add Users to Role".
				A pop-up window will appear.  Check the users you wish to add and click "Add Users". The Role Detail Information portlet
				will be populated with the selected users.	
				</p>
				<p>			
				TODO: screenshot of the pop-up window		
				</p>			
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Remove Checked Users">
				<p>
				To remove a user from a role, select the user(s) you wish to remove and click on the "Remove Checked Users" button.
				Be aware that this action is permanent!				
				</p>
				<p>			
				TODO: screenshot of Remove Checked Users button		
				</p>				
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Search Users in Role">
				<p>
				You can search for a particular user by entering the users name or part of the users name in the search text box.
				After clicking on the "Search" button, the "Users in Role" listing will show the search results, starting with the user that
				best matched your search query, followed by increasingly less matching users.
				</p>
				<p>				
				TODO: screenshot of search text box and button 			
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Filter Users in Role">
				<p>
				To get only exact matches when searching for (or part of) a particular user name, check the "filter" checkbox below the
				search text box.
				</p>
				<p>				
				TODO: screenshot of the filter check box 			
				</p>
			</subsection>			
		</section>	
		<subsection name="Role Details Configuration">
			<p>
			For some weird reason there is no Edit Mode here!	
				<table>
				<tr>
				<th>Field</th>
				<th>Description</th>			
				</tr>
				<tr>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
				<td></td>
				<td></td>
				</tr>
				</table>
			</p>		
		</subsection>				
	</body>
</document>