<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>About Jetspeed Users Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Using Jetspeed</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
    <body>
        <section name="About this guide">
			<p>
				This User guide is designed for people who are new to Jetspeed or as a reference for navigating
				through the Jetspeed interface while logged in as a regular user.  This guide is meant to be
				a foundation for those who wish to continue with the Admin guide, Deployers guide and
				Developers guide. Some concepts, such as security, may cross several guides but will be
				structured for the Role of that particular guide.
			</p>
			<p>
				After reading this guide, the user will be able to:
				<ul>
					<li>Create a new user</li>
					<li>Login to Jetspeed</li>
					<li>Request a forgotten password</li>
					<li>Change the language used in Jetspeed</li>
					<li>Minimize, maximize and restore portlet windows</li>
					<li>Edit a portlet's preferences</li>
					<li>Add, move and remove portlets</li>
					<li>Change the decorators of Jetspeed</li>
					<li>Change the decorators of individual portlets</li>
					<li>Create and delete tabs</li>
					<li>Create and delete folders</li>
					<li>Navigate through menu's and pages</li>
					<li>Use breadcrumbs to navigate folders</li>
					<li>Switch between Jetpeed desktop and portal</li>
					<li>Use Jetspeed desktop</li>
					<li>Logout of Jetspeed</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			<subsection name="User Guide">
			<p>
				The User guide will not cover aspects relating to the Admin guide, Deployers guide or Developers
				guide.  The User guide will focus on introducing the user to the means to log into the portal, navigate
				within the portal and customize the look and feel of the portal.  A definitions page is included
				for important words or concepts that will make the guide more understandable for those unfamiliar with
				Portal's or Jetspeed.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Admin Guide">
			<p>
				The Admin guide will not cover topics addressed in the User guide. This guide will be focused on any
				configuration and managment options that can be altered while Jetspeed is running.  The administrator
				will have full access to configuring users, groups and roles through the administrative portlets.  
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Deployers Guide">		
			<p>
				The Deployers guide will not cover topics addressed in the User or Admin guide. This guide will address
				Administrative and Configuration tasks that can not occur while Jetspeed is running.  A section of this guide
				will be dedicated to deploying Jetspeed on Websphere.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Developers Guide">
			<p>
				The Developers guide will not cover topics addressed in the User, Admin or Deployers guide.
			</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
 	</body>
</document>