<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Users Guide Definitions</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Using Jetspeed</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Definitions">
			<p>
				Definitions and concepts mentioned in User Guide are listed here for reference.   
			</p>
			<subsection name="Decorator">
				<p>
					The portal design, or skins, are known in Jetspeed as decorators.  They can also be referred to as Themes.<br/>
					<img src="images/decoratordiagram.png"/>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Portal">
			<p>
				"A portal is a web based application that 
				commonly-provides personalization, single 
				sign on, content aggregation from different 
				sources and hosts the presentation layer of 
				Information Systems. Aggregation is the action 
				of integrating content from different 
				sources within a web page. A portal may have 
				sophisticated personalization features to 
				provide customized content to users. Portal 
				pages may have different set of portlets 
				creating content for different users." JSR-168:PLT.2.1
			</p>
			<p>
					A portal based on Jetspeed can make applications, database information
					and other data sources available to end-users through a single web site.
					Jetspeed provides a security infrastructure so that the information and
					functions made available to each user can be customized on basis of the
					user or a role that the user has. The user can access the portal via a
					web browser, WAP-phone, pager or any other device supported by the
					servlet engine.	
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Portlet">
				<p>
					"A portlet is a Java technology based web component, managed by a 
					portlet container, that processes requests and generates dynamic content. 
					Portlets are used by portals as pluggable user interface components that 
					provide a presentation layer to Information Systems." JSR-168:PLT.2.2 
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Portlet Window Diagram">
				<p>
					<img src="images/portletwindowdiagram.png"/>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Roles">
			<p>
				Roles are the persona users can take on when interacting with the system.  This allows
				the system to define behaviors by role, not by individual users.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Tiled Window">
			<p>
				A tiled window in Jetspeed is a window that does not overlap any other windows.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			A tiled window in Jetspeed is a window that does not overlap any other windows
			<subsection name="Window States">
			<p>
			Window States indicate the amount of the portal page 
			space that will be assigned to the generated 
			content of a portlet. 
				<ul>
					<li>Normal - indicates the portlet may be sharing the rendering of the page.</li>
					<li>Minimized - the portlet should only render minimal or no output at all.</li>
					<li>Maximized - indicates the portlet that the portlet may be the only portlet being rendered. A portlet may generate richer content in this state.</li>
				</ul>
				</p>
				</subsection>
		</section>
 	</body>
</document>