<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Users Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Using Jetspeed</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Welcome to Jetspeed">
			<p>				
				Jetspeed is an Open Portal Platform and Enterprise Information Portal, written entirely in open source under the Apache license in Java and XML. Jetspeed is an open component portal architecture based on standards. All access to the portal is managed through a robust portal security policy. Within a Jetspeed portal, individual portlets can be aggregated to create a page. Each portlet is an independent application with Jetspeed acting as the central hub making information from multiple sources available in an easy to use manner.
			</p>
			<p>
				A portal based on Jetspeed can make applications, database information and other data sources available to end-users through a single web site. Jetspeed provides a security infrastructure so that the information and functions made available to each user can be customized on basis of the user or a role that the user has. The user can access the portal via a web browser, WAP-phone, pager or any other device supported by the servlet engine. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Users can personalize their experience, by adding new content with 
				portlet customizers, styling their view with portal decorators (skins) 
				and layouts. Personalization blends with secure access to provide a 
				custom view of the portal based on runtime customizations and 
				parameters.
			</p>
			<p>
				Jetspeed provides the following personalization features: 
				<ul>
				<li>Portlet Selector (search for portlets, add portlets, categorize portlets)</li>
				<li>Portal Customizer (move portlets, choose decorations, layouts) </li>
				<li>Desktop Customizer (same as portal, drag and drop, resizing, detach) </li>
				<li>Portlet API Preferences Editors </li>
				<li>Administrative Customization </li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</section>
 	</body>
</document>