<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Users Guide - Navigation</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Using Jetspeed</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Navigating the Portal">
			<p>
				Tabbed Menus, Breadcrumbs and Menu Items are the main ways to Navigate through your portal. Edit, Help and other portlet bar action items can
				display different screens, but you have not navigated to a new location. Customization of all navigation items can be configured by the
				Administrator of the portal.  
			</p>
			<subsection name="Tabbed Menus">
			<p>
				Tabbed menus across the top contain selections for each page found in the current folder. The current Tabs may have come pre-configured as standard or may have been created and configured by the user. Each Tab 
				can be configured with a different Theme, Layout, Portlet Theme and different Portlets.
			</p>	
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Breadcrumbs">
			<p> 
				Breadcrumbs are located just below the Tabbed Menus. Breadcrumbs give you a visual representation of the path you have
				taken to reach your current location.  From the breadcrumb trail, you can navigate back out of the folder hierarchy up to previous 
				destinations.  
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Menu Items">
			<p>
				Menu Items are located in the Left Hand side menu. Each one of these links can take you to a location within the Portal or to an external
				location such as a website. Folders you have created will appear in this menu.
		 	</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
 	</body>
</document>