<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Users Guide</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Using Jetspeed</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Portlets">
			<p>
				While in the edit mode of the portal window, you will notice that each portlet on your page now has several options to customize.  A drop down menu option for changing your decorator of that individual portlet, 
				an icon (ICON**********) for removing the portlet or arrows for moving the portlet one location spot in the direction of the arrow. Menus 
				will not be displayed for resources that are not accessible.
			</p>
			<p>
				
				Screenshot of drop down portlet theme, remove icon and move icons.
			</p>
			<subsection name="Moving Portlets">
			<p>	
				Depending upon their current placement in the window, arrows will be available to move your portlets across
				columns or up and down within a column. Portlets will auto-adjust for each move.
				Screenshot of portlet moving left before and after
			</p>
			<p>
				Each portlet can have it's own decorator that will override the decorator selected in the portal window section.  
				However, choosing a new theme in the Page/Folder Customizer will change all portlets to that theme regardless 
				if they have been given individual themes. You will need to change the individual portlet themes again to have 
				the portlets display their own if you have set the theme globally.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Removing Portlets">
			<p>	
				To remove a portlet from your window, click on the (ICON REMOVE******************) icon of the portlet you wish to remove.  The remaining portlets
				will adjust to fill the space if any are lower in the same column.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Adding Portlets">
			<p>	
				(screen shot of add portlets locations)<br/>
				Click on Add Portlet.<br/>
				screenshot of Portlet Selector.<br/>
				The Portlet Selector shows the portlets that are available to be added.  There are multiple pages that you may navigate through by using the
				(screenshot of 1,2,3 last next).  There is also a search field where you can search for a portlet by name.  The portlets are 
				separated into categories as well.<br/>
				The portlet selector displays the name of the portlet, a brief description, an Add option and a counter of how many instances
				of this portlet are currently running.  Clicking on the Add link will increase the counter by 1, but no other visible changes will 
				occur at this time.
			</p>
			<p>
				Clicking on the [GoBack] option or arrow will bring you to the original customization window where you can see your portlets have been added
				to your portlet window.  If you have changed your decorator from the default decorator, you may find that your new portlets are using a 
				different decorator rather than the decorator you are now using.
			</p>
			<p>
				You will need to return at one point to the original customization window before you see the restore option to leave the configuration
				area. 
			</p>
			</subsection>
			<p>			
				Click on the restore icon next to the logout button to return to normal view and see your changes.
			</p>
		</section>
 	</body>
</document>