<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
    
    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
    
    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Jetspeed Users Guide - Portlet Modes</title>
		<subtitle>Guide to Using Jetspeed</subtitle>
		<authors>
			<person name="David Sean Taylor" email="taylor@apache.org" />
			<person name="Jody McAlister" email="jmcalister@onehippo.com" />
		</authors>
	</properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Portlet Modes and Action Bar">
        <subsection name="Portlet Modes">
			<p>
				Portlet Modes indicate the function that a portlet is 
				performing. A portlet mode advises a portlet what task it 
				should perform. Availability of portlet modes may be 
				restricted based on user roles. 
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>View - general portlet rendering and interaction. </li>
				<li>Edit - customization the behavior of a portlet, update preferences. </li>
				<li>Help - provides context-sensitive help for this portlet. </li>
				<li>Custom Portlet Modes - vendor specific.</li>
			</ul>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Portlet Action Bar">
			<p>
				The portlet action bar <img align="top" src="images/editactionbar.png"/>
			</p>
			<p>
				<img align="top" src="images/editicon.png"/> The edit icon will change the portlet window to display configurable preferences for that particular portlet.  For instance, a weather portlet can give you the options to change the city it is displaying as well as other options.  Each portlet will have unique preferences.  It is possible to have two or more of the same portlets displayed, but each will use it's own set of preferences.  This would allow you to have two weather portlets displaying the weather for two different cities.
			</p>
			<p>
				<img align="top" src="images/helpicon.png"/> The help icon will display a page that display detailed information on how to use the portlet, version numbers or anything the developer has chosen to display in this page.
			</p>
			<p>
				<img align="top" src="images/minicon.png"/> The minimize icon will reduce your portlet down to displaying the title bar of the portlet only.  <img align="top" src="images/restoreicon.png"/> You can click on the restore which is available to return the portlet to it's original window state.
			</p>
			<p>
				<img align="top" src="images/maxicon.png"/> The maximize icon will enlarge the portlet to display only that portlet in your portal window.  <img align="top" src="images/restoreicon.png"/> The restore button will be available again when in this mode.  
			</p>
			<p>
				Other icons that you may see in the icon bar are <img align="top" src="images/printicon.png"/> print and other customized icons.
			</p>
		</subsection>
		</section>
 	</body>
</document>